<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse upon I Peter IV., VIII wherein the power and efficacy of charity as it is a means to procure the pardon of sin is explained and vindicated / by John Whitefoot.</title>
            <author>Whitefoote, John, 1610-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1862</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26478</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09479560</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09479560</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43236</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65814)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43236)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1319:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse upon I Peter IV., VIII wherein the power and efficacy of charity as it is a means to procure the pardon of sin is explained and vindicated / by John Whitefoot.</title>
                  <author>Whitefoote, John, 1610-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>139 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Hayes for William Graves and are to sold by Samuel Oliver,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge [Cambridgeshire] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: Charity a means to procure pardon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st, IV, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Charity.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:43236:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43236:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 18. 1694.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gul. Stanley</hi> Procan.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joſ. Beaumont.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joh. Mountagu.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Eachard.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joh. Covel.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43236:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE UPON I <hi>Peter</hi> IV. VIII. Wherein the Power and Efficacy OF CHARITY. As it is a Means to procure the <hi>Pardon</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> Is EXPLAINED and VINDICATED,</p>
            <p>By the Reverend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Whitefoot,</hi> Sen. of <hi>NORWICH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Hayes,</hi> For <hi>William Graves,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Samuel Oliver,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>NORWICH.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:43236:3"/>
            <p>TO <hi>All Good Christians, whoſe Faith is made Effectual by</hi> CHARITY, The AUTHOR <hi>Dedicateth this</hi> DISCOURSE; <hi>Wiſhing Them Increaſe of that moſt Divine, moſt Chriſtian, and moſt Spiritual Grace.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43236:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Pet. 4. 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And above all things have fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Charity among your ſelves, for Charity ſhall <hi>(or will)</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a multitude of Sins.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in the Ethnick Theology of the Greek Poets, we read of a Famous Triade of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, reported to be the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Jupiter:</hi> So the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> makes mention of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Trinity of Chriſtian Graces, all ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Fruits and Daughters of the Holy Spirit. 1 Cor. 13.13. <hi>And now abideth Faith, Hope, and Charity, but the greateſt of theſe is Charity.</hi> And that may duely be eſteemed the greater, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43236:4"/>of the Three, in many reſpects, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that which the Apoſtle ſeems ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to aim at, in that Text, <hi>viz.</hi> That of continuance and duration in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Life, after the Expiration of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Two. For Charity is a Vertue of the greateſt Perfection that can be, and moſt highly deſerving the Name of Grace. <hi>Gratia gratis data, &amp; gratia gratum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciens;</hi> As freely given as any other and moſt gratefull to God and Man. This Charity is the Root, Ground, and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all Chriſtian Piety, as is inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated by the words of the Apoſtle, Eph. 3.17, 18.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Radicati &amp; Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dati.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That ye, being rooted and grounded in love,</hi> &amp;c. It is indeed the end, and fruit of the other Two. Faith teaches it, Hope excites and cheriſhes it. It is alſo of greateſt Extent, extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both to God and Man; All Men, our ſelves, our Friends, and Enemies. Faith and Hope will be antiquated by poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſight, and fruition, but Charity is a thing that we ſhall carry with us into the other World, where we ſhall improve and keep it for ever. <hi>'Tis the end of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.5. and <hi>the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43236:4"/>of the Law.</hi> Gal. 5.14. For <hi>all the Law is fulfilled in one word, even in this, Thou ſhalt love,</hi> &amp;c. That one little Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſyllable Love, is a perfect abbreviation of the whole <hi>Code</hi> and <hi>Pandects</hi> of the Divine Law. The firſt and the great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment is this,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.37, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart and with all thy ſoul, with all thy mind, and with all thy might.</hi> And the Second is like unto it, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf: On theſe two Commandments hang all the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that truly loves God, will not break any of his Commandments willfully; and he that doth not love him, cannot keep any of them.
<note place="margin">1 Jo 5.3.</note> 'Tis this love that keeps us from tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing the Law, and ſo prevents ſin, and (as I ſhall ſhew hereafter) the ſame is uſefull to cover ſin, and to procure the pardon thereof. It keeps us from inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or offending our neighbour, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines us to forgive his offences againſt us.</p>
            <p>'Tis <hi>the bond of perfection,</hi> both of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Grace, of Humanity and Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: A loving Diſpoſition is that which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43236:5"/>we call Good Nature, the moſt Ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Noble, and Amiable. Whereas the want of it, and eſpecially the contraries to it; an envious, malicious, peeviſh, fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, rigid, cruel, covetous, and penuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mind, is Ill Nature, Diſingenuous and Hatefull.</p>
            <p>Therefore the extream oppoſite to Love, beareth the name of Wickedneſs in an Emphatical Senſe, in the Greek and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, as alſo in our own, and other Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, that have any Derivation from them. So the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>malitia, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> are generally uſed. And the Spirit of wickedneſs, or the wicked Spirit is called by the name of <hi>Satan,</hi> which ſignifies an abſolute privation of all Love to God or Man together with the oppoſite to both, conſiſting in his enmity to both.</p>
            <p>But Charity <hi>is Goodneſs it ſelf,</hi> in the Common Senſe of that Word, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it there is no ſuch thing as Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs truly ſo called. And whereas there are divers ſorts of Goodneſs, noted by the ordinary diſtinction of <hi>Bonum jucundum, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, &amp; honeſtum; the pleaſant, profitable, and honeſt Good,</hi> Charity comprehends them all in the greateſt Perfection: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43236:5"/>ſo pleaſant both to the Lover, and the Beloved, nothing ſo Profitable to both, nothing ſo Honourable.</p>
            <p>'Tis <hi>the Perfection of Righteouſneſs</hi> in the Senſe of Holy Scripture, where the word Righteous,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.1. ſome Copies read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Righteouſneſs for Alms.</note> and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs do moſt frequently ſignifie (eſpecially in the <hi>Pſalms</hi>) more than meer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, or common Juſtice. Nor is the Senſe of them to be contracted into the ſhort and ſcanty meaſures of the Cardinal Vertue in the Ethick Philoſopher, or the Definition of <hi>Juſtinian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Juſtitia eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans, &amp; perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua voluntas ſuum cuique tribuendi.</note> Though even that might paſs for a Definition good enough, with a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Gloſs, borrowed from S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> and our Saviours command, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7, 8. <hi>Render to all their due,</hi> where Love is one (and the chiefeſt of all) made ſo by the Common Law of Nature, and by the expreſs Precept of our Saviour of loving our Neighbour as our ſelves, which makes it a general debt, ſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by the Apoſtle, <hi>Owe nothing to any man but to love one another.</hi> And if this Obligation of debt, could be diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43236:6"/>with, or abſtracted from this Act of Charity in men, as it is in God, it would have ſo much the more of Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as being more free. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> calls it <hi>Piety,</hi> or Godlineſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.4. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>James</hi> makes it <hi>Pure Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. To ſhew Piety at home, he means Charity.</note> Ja.</hi> 1, 27. <hi>Pure Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and undefiled before God, and the Father is this; to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit the fatherleſs, and the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows in their diſtreſs.</hi> And the ſame He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies both Charitable and Godly.</p>
            <p>It is <hi>the Energy, Life, and Perfection of Faith.</hi> Theſe are all Apoſtolical Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles. <hi>vid. Gal.</hi> 5.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.18, 21, 26. I do not add the Scholaſtick Notion, that it is the form of Faith, becauſe that's liable to ſome Quarrel.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude the preſent Encomium of this Grace, in Three Words: ſhewing that it is <hi>the moſt Divine, the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, the moſt Spiritual Vertue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <q rend="margQuotes">1. <hi>The moſt Divine,</hi> For God is Love, ſaith the moſt Loving, and beloved Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple twice over in one Chapter, 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.7, 8, 16. Beloved let us love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43236:6"/>for Love is of God, And every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God. He that loveth not, knoweth not God, for God is Love. And we have known and believed the Love that God hath to us: God is Love, and he that dwelleth in Love, dwelleth in God, and God in him.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So did ſome of the oldeſt of the Greek Poets call the Supream Deity, and the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal of all Beings by the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Love.</hi> And ſo <hi>Plato</hi> and his Diſciples call the Firſt Perſon in their Trinity <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſelf goodneſs.</hi> 'Tis by this Vertue of Love, that we are made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the Divine Nature moſt eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that being the Higheſt Perfection of the Image of God, that we are capable of: For God is Love, not cauſally only, but eſſentially. Other Graces are from him,
<note place="margin">Quicquid in Deo eſt, Deus eſt.</note> but this is in him; and whatſoever is ſo, is himſelf. Other Graces of Humility, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, and even thoſe two mentioned by the Apoſtle together with this, Faith, and Hope, do connotate ſomething of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, incompetible to the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: But Love is Pure, and Perfect Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43236:7"/>Our Engliſh Name of God comes from Good. And 'tis obſervable from <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6. where the name of God is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed by himſelf, moſt of the Royal Titles that make up the Dignity and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of that Great Name, are no other than a Comment upon this ſimple and Eſſential Attribute of Love; <q rend="margQuotes">The Lord paſſed by before him <hi>(Moſes)</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, The Lord, the Lord God, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, and gracious, long-ſuffering, and abundant in Goodneſs and Truth, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy for Thouſands, forgiving ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, tranſgreſſion, and ſin.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And 'tis this Vertue of Love that makes us partakers of the Name of God in a qualified ſenſe, <hi>Homo homini Deus, one man is a petty God to another,</hi> as he is a Benefactor. Such only were the Hero's, and minor Deities of the Heathens: Such as had been Eminent Benefactors to their Country in their Lives, and were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Deified after their Death. Such were all earthly Gods, Kings, and Princes, they were called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Benefactors.</hi> Luke 22.25. So the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> uſed for a Prince, and rendred by the Septuagint <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth primarily ſignifie a Liberal Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Benefactor.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43236:7"/>
            <p>I ſay therefore, that Love is the moſt Divine Grace, as having moſt of the Name, and Nature of God in it. On the contrary, thoſe Vicious Diſpoſitions, which are moſt directly oppoſite to Love, are the moſt Satanical and Diabolical, malice, hatred, envy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Charity is the moſt Chriſtian Virtue,</hi> moſt ſtrictly charged by Chriſt himſelf, by his ſpecial Command, and ſignally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in his Singular Example, <hi>Jo.</hi> 15.12. <hi>This is my Commandment that ye love one another, as I have loved you.</hi> The Pronoun <hi>my,</hi> is Emphatical, ſignifying the Special Weight that he puts upon this Commandment. And this is the reaſon, (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Hierom</hi> reports) that was given by the Beloved Diſciple S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John,</hi> when the queſtion was put to him by his Auditors, why he did ſo much in ulcate that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in his Preaching, <hi>Filioli diligite al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terutrum,</hi> Little children love one another; he anſwered. <hi>quia eſt preceptum Domini,</hi> becauſe it was the Command of his Lord, meaning the Special and Principal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, and that, which being obeyed, would ſecure the fulfilling of all the reſt, that concerned humane ſociety; and was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43236:8"/>moſt neceſſary for the Conſtitution, and the Preſervation of the Church. Indeed all Societies are maintained by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cement of Amity, nor can any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt without it. But the Chriſtian Society was deſigned to be the moſt Perfect of any that was poſſible to be amongſt men and therefore was neceſſary to be moſt ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obliged to this Bond of Perfection. And therefore,</p>
            <p>This precept of Charity was by Chriſt perfected in the proper meaſures and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications thereof, and to be extended to all Mankind without exception of enemies, which by no other law of Heathens or Jews had been expreſsly required. <hi>Amicos diligere omnium eſt, inimicos ſolorum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum,</hi> Tertul. To love friends was a common acknowledged obligation and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of all men, but to love Enemies too, was a pure Chriſtian law, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.34.
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.44.</note> 
               <hi>A new commandment I give unto you, that ye love one another, as I have loved you.</hi> He calls it a new Commandment, notwithſtanding it was as old as any other, as old as <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Adam,</hi> as to the matter and ſubſtance of it: but almoſt antiquated by the manners of men,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43236:8"/>and not well underſtood by the Jews, and therefore was renewed by him, who was the great Reformer of the world, by his precept and example. And this mutual love and amity was aſſigned by Him, to be the badge and cogniſance, or mark of his Diſciples, whereby they ſhould be known and diſtinguiſhed from other People. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.35. <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my Diſciples, if ye love one another.</hi> And accordingly this was obſerved in the primitive times, as the ſignal mark and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Chriſtians, as is teſtified by <hi>Tertullian</hi> or <hi>Minutius Felix, Vide, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiunt, ut invicem ſe diligunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Love is the moſt Spiritual Grace.</hi> 'Tis the firſt fruit of the Spirit in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. <hi>The fruit of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is Love, &amp;c.</hi> And the reſt that are added, are no other then the known effects, and ſymptoms of Love. <hi>The fruits of the Spirit are Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Meckneſs, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis the diſtinct character and proper attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of the Holy Spirit, as that name ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the Third Perſon in the Bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. The three Primalities, or ſignal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties noted in the Trinity of Perſons, are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43236:9"/>Power belonging to the Father Almighty, Wiſdome to the Son, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in whom are hid all the Treaſures of wiſdom and knowledge;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.3.</note> and Love to the Holy Ghoſt, which is that which conſummates the perfection of the Divine Nature, rendring it infinitely good, as well as great, powerfull and wiſe. And this Infinite Goodneſs is the flower and ultimate glory of the Divine Nature, crowning his wiſdom and power. So that as the Firſt Perſon in the Trinity may be eſteemed the moſt Excellent, in as much as it is the fountain and baſis of the whole Deity, and of all Being: And the Second Perſon repreſented by the title of Wiſdom, called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ratio prima eſt ſubſtantialis,</hi> is the firſt natural Emergency, or advance of the ſame Being, and therefore called the Son: So the Third Perſon which is expreſſed by Love, and is the immediate principle of all communication of Being and Goodneſs, may in that reſpect be ſaid to be <hi>flos &amp; gloria Deitatis,</hi> the flower, and glory, and perfection of the whole Deity: as the word Glory doth properly ſignifie, <hi>the manifeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and illuſtration of any Excellency.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:43236:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>NOW the Text that I am treating of is an Exhortation to this <hi>moſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, moſt Chriſtian, moſt Spiritual Vertue,</hi> emphatically expreſſed as a matter of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Concern. <hi>Above all things have fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Charity among your ſelves;</hi> And then urged with a ſtrong argument or motive drawn from a ſpecial Effect and Conſequent thereof, <hi>For Charity ſhall cover a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Deſign of my preſent Diſcourſe is chiefly upon this particular Argument or Motive; which being well underſtood, and firmly believed, may be enough to ſave me the labour of adding many more found in other Texts, ſome of which have been briefly touched in the foregoing Chapter, and all, or moſt of them amply ſet forth by others,
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Iſ Barrow.</hi>
                  </note> eſpecially by a late worthy Perſon in his excellent Sermon upon the Subject of Charity. Whereas that particular Argument which is alledged in this Text (though it may have been mentioned by others) hath not, to my knowledge, been ſo diſtinctly and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43236:10"/>largely diſcuſſed, as the Weight and Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of it ſeems to deſerve. There being no argument or motive to the practice of this Vertue, more like to prevail with perſons, ſenſible of the multitude and danger of their ſins, than this, if it may be admitted in the Senſe hereafter declared. For this is moſt notoriouſly known to have been the greateſt, and moſt effectual Motive to that one common and eminent branch of this great Vertue, that hath in vulgar Speech monopolized the name of Charity, <hi>viz.</hi> that of Alms and Beneficence. This one ſimple Motive ſpecified in this Text, hath (I believe) prevailed more to this effect in all parts of Chriſtendom, with all ſorts of Perſons, in their life time, and at their death, than all the reſt. And this eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with ſuch People, as being much ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of their ſins, have deſired to verifie the truth of their Repentance, by bringing forth fruits worthy of it. Amongſt which there is none to be compared to the works of Charity.</p>
               <p>Though indeed there be many other Fruits worthy of repentance, in a juſt ſenſe, but not equal to this. Such are all acts and works of extraordinary Devotion, all pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43236:10"/>of Pennance and Mortification, which the Apoſtle calls <hi>judging of our ſelves,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.31. And <hi>Revenge,</hi> proceeding from a Godly ſorrow, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. The Schoolmen from the Latine Fathers, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> expreſs them by the word <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> an innocent word, if rightly interpreted. Theſe are ſuch as do chiefly conſiſt in Faſting, Watching, and Afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the body by abſtinence from lawfull In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, with various expreſſions of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netential Sorrows for ſin, and Subjugation of carnal luſts:
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calls <hi>keeping under the Body, and bringing it under ſubjection,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.27. <hi>Not ſparing the Body,</hi> Col 2.23.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Bodily Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe</hi> he calls it elſewhere, and acknowledges it to be <hi>profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> though but a little in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of true Godlineſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. Hereunto belongs all that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>hard uſage of the Body,</hi> practiſed by the <hi>Aſceticks</hi> in the ancient Church, eſpecially in the Eaſt, where the ſeverities of Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Life began, and moſt prevailed, in their courſe Diet, hard Lodging, and Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Sackcloth and Haircloth. The
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43236:11"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Humicubation,</hi> lying upon the ground, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which things have been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, and ſtill are in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Churches.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being cleared from that Superſtition, which they are liable to, in the kinds and meaſures of them, as alſo from ſuch Hypocriſie as was practiſed by the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, and is notorious in the later Ages of the Church, are not to be rejected, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to be proper and reaſonable fruits and teſtimonies of Repentance, as exerciſe of Self diſcipline, and <hi>judging our ſelves that we may not be judged,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.31.</p>
               <p>There are a multitude of Texts in the Old Teſtament, wherein ſuch Afflicting of our ſelves, in teſtimony of repentance, are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly approved, but expreſly enjoyned by God himſelf,
<note place="margin">Lev. 16.29, 31. cap. 23.27, 32. Numb 29.7. Ezr. 8.21. Iſa. 58.3.</note> as may be ſeen in the Texts quoted in the Margin, &amp; many others that might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And that this was no point of meer <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and Ceremonial Diſcipline, may be confirmed from the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples before quoted, particularly from St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in his own practice, and the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.17.</note> and the expreſs precept of St.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43236:11"/>
                  <hi>James,</hi> Cap. 4.9. <hi>Be afflicted, and mourn, and weep.</hi> Such affliction, as naturally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the affection of Sorrow, whiles we are mixt Creatures, conſiſting of Body as well as Soul, may be either impoſed for ſatisfaction of Scandal, and teſtimony of Repentance, or voluntarily undertaken and practiſed by true Penitents to expreſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, their Humiliation and Godly ſorrow.</p>
               <p>But none of theſe things are in their kind ſuch worthy fruits of Repentance, or ſo acceptable to God, as the ſpecial exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of Charity: Becauſe none of them have any ſuch intrinſick Goodneſs in them, as is oppoſite to the Evil repented of, or can be reaſonably preſumed to balance it, none ſo available as Charity for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or expiation of the ſin (pardon that Word for the preſent, which I ſhall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret afterward in ſuch a Senſe, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be nothing prejudicial to the Expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation by the Blood of Chriſt.) Charity is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herefore moſt acceptable to God, becauſe moſt beneficial to Men, and moſt agreeable to his own natural and eſſential Goodneſs. Therefore doth God prefer Mercy, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s but a branch of Charity, before Sacrifice
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43236:12"/>and all manner of outward Worſhip, not Ceremonial only, but alſo Moral and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, as of Prayers and Praiſes. <hi>Vid. Iſa.</hi> 1. v. 11. to the 19. <hi>To relieve the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to judge the fatherleſs, and to plead for the widow,</hi> are named for things ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and prevalent with God, that he promiſeth an intire pardon of the groſſeſt ſins, to all them that joyn theſe things with the Eſſential duties of Repentance, expreſſed ver. 16. <q rend="margQuotes">Waſh ye, make ye clean, put away the evil of your doings from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mine Eyes, ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well, ſeek Judgment, relieve the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, judge the Fatherleſs, plead for the Widow; Come now let us reaſon to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſaith the Lord, though your ſins be as ſcarlet, they ſhall be white as ſnow, though they be like crimſon, they ſhall be as wooll;</q> that is, the deepeſt dye and ſtain of them ſhall be quite taken out. But of this more hereafter.</p>
               <p>Come we now to the expreſs Doctrine o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Apoſtle in the words of the Text <hi>Charity doth, will, or ſhall cover a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſins.</hi> Such a variation of Lection i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> found in the <hi>Greek</hi> Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> aliàs <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but the difference is not conſiderable.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:43236:12"/>
               <p>Now concerning the nature of Charity, with the Extent and various Effects thereof. Though I might preſume them to be ſo well known to any Reader, that will be capable of underſtanding the future Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, (deſigned to be as plain as I am able to make it) as makes it unneceſſary to give any large Deſcription thereof, yet do I not judge it altogether needleſs to give any Account at all of it.</p>
               <p>Briefly then, Charity, or Love relating to our Neighbour (as by the expreſs words of the Text it doth) is not to be confined to that one eminent Branch thereof, which conſiſts only in Alms, or works of Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, becauſe theſe are things, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly may be done without any true Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 Cor. 13.8. <hi>Though I give all my goods to feed the Poor, and have not Charity</hi> (which Suppoſition were abſurd, if it were ſimply impoſſible) <hi>it profiteth me nothing.</hi> Vain-glory, carnal and worldly Ends and Intereſt, may utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the notion and vertue of Charity in ſuch Works. And 'tis poſſible for a man to exerciſe ſome acts of pretended Charity, to ſuch ends as are utterly repugnant to the Nature of it, as when they are done of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43236:13"/>purpoſe to corrupt the Minds and Manners of them, upon whom they are beſtowed, to entice them to Iniquity, and to ſerve the ends of the Donor, to the prejudice of the Receiver.</p>
               <p>And where none of theſe things are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, a man may yet be otherwiſe as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of true Charity, as the Devil is, and as much tainted with thoſe <hi>Vicioſities,</hi> that are moſt contrary to it; Malice, Envy, Pride, Cruelty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet ſeem to be Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his Alms. On the contrary, a true and acceptable Charity may exiſt without them: I mean without the outward Works, and that only in caſe of Inability to afford them, or want of Objects to receive them; for otherwiſe the Diſpoſition and Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mind to afford them according to Ability, and opportunity, is in ſeparable from any true and real Charity.</p>
               <p>This poſſible Miſtake, grounded upon a vulgar uſe of the Word, being prevented, I ſay, That Charity in the due extent of its Notion comprehends all the Good, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all the Evil that our Neighbour is capable of receiving from us; or that we are capable of intending or extending to him. Charity ſignifies all the benefit that is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43236:13"/>deſirable from one Man to another. All that can profit or reaſonably pleaſe him, all that can any way better his Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, preſent or future: The Acts of it are as various and numerous, as are the needs, or capacities of advantage and benefit by our Neighbour in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kind. To conclude,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.10.</note> Charity imports an averſion or declining of all manner of Evil to him in Thought, Word or Deed, all <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection</hi> to him, all <hi>Miſpeaking</hi> of him, or to him, and all <hi>Miſdoing.</hi> And not only all ſorts of Injuries, but all Unkindneſſes, inward of will and affections, and outward of words, actions and geſtures.</p>
               <p>He that deſires any more Particular Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of this Vertue, may find it ſet forth in that known Chapter of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Pauls</hi> firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> Chap. 13. And all that moſt exactly abridged by that General Precept of our Saviour, of <hi>doing to others as we would be done to:</hi> only the word <hi>do,</hi> is therein to be extended as well to thoughts, and words, as to any ſort of outward actions: agreeable to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe of the ſame word in our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, applied to thoughts and words, as well as deeds, whilſt we ſay, we do
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43236:14"/>think, and we do Love, and we do ſpeak. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Whatever ye</hi> do <hi>in word, or deed do all in the name of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed thoughts and words are the moſt Peculiar of Humane Acts. This Precept, I ſay, in the due extent of it, rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted, by the Rules and Meaſures of a reaſonable will (which only can be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in the ſentence) is the moſt Perfect Rule of Humane Equity, that can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in words, comprehending alſo the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Perfection of Chriſtian Charity.</p>
               <p>Having now premiſed this brief De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Vertue of Charity, I come to the Particular Argument, or Motive, whereby it is urged by the Apoſtle in this Text. <hi>Charity ſhall cover a multitude of ſins.</hi> And here I am to ſpeak by way of Explication and Confirmation.</p>
               <p>By way of Explication, I ſhall make theſe three Inquiries,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Whoſe ſins they are which the Apoſtle means will be covered by Charity?</p>
               <p>Secondly, What's meant by the cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſins?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, What ſort of ſins will be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by Charity, and under what Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitations?</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43236:14"/>
               <p>After I ſhall have given a Competent Explication of the Propoſition, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of theſe Queſtions, I ſhall Confirm the General Doctrine from other Texts of Scripture, with ſome Allegations of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and then anſwer ſome Objections, like to be made againſt that Interpretation of the Text, which I ſhall pitch upon, and againſt the General Doctrine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by aſſerted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP II.</head>
               <p>§. 1. I Am to begin with the firſt Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> Whoſe ſins they are, which will be covered by Charity? And here I find Interpreters differing: ſome under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancing the ſins of others, to whom the Charity is extended: which is the ſenſe accepted by moſt Proteſtants, and ſome <hi>Pontificians:</hi> And ſome, the ſins of the Charitable Perſon, which (for the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons hereafter to be advanced) ſeems to me moſt probable, and ſpecially intended by the Apoſtle in this Text. Some alſo taking in both ſenſes, not without reaſon, becauſe ſo the Sentence is undoubtedly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43236:15"/>true: Charity, eſpecially, if it be ſervent, will cover a multitude of ſins, both in the Charitable Perſon (as ſhall be afterward confirmed) and in other men to whom it is exerciſed. And ſo both Senſes are but diſtinct <hi>Verifications</hi> of the ſame words, taken in the greateſt amplitude of ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and containing in each Senſe a ſtrong motive to enforce the preceding Exhortation, <hi>Above all things have fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent charity, for,</hi> &amp;c. Wherefore although I do in my own judgement prefer the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Senſe, as moſt ſpecially intended by the Apoſtle, and that is the main Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Deſign of my Diſcourſe; yet I ſhall not wholly neglect the other Senſe importing a ſpecial Effect, and Branch o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that Charity, which is here recommende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to all Chriſtians, with the promiſe, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> declaration of ſo great a Reward, as the covering of a multitude of ſins in him than hath it; which is that Senſe of the word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that I inſiſt upon, not only as the ſtrongeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Motive to enforce the Exhortation, but alſo as moſt agreeable to the Context i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this place.</p>
               <p n="1">I. This Senſe, if it may be allowed in the matter of it, to expreſs a certain truth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43236:15"/>(as I doubt not to prove, paſt all doubt, from other Texts) affords a Motive to the inforcement of the Apoſtles Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo much more ſtrong and effectual than the other Senſe, as the covering of a multitude of a mans own fins, is a greater Benefit to him, than the covering of any multitude of other mens ſins can be; and therefore the hopes of it, muſt needs be moſt prevalent with any man that hath not more Charity for his Neighbour, than he hath for himſelf. Whereas therefore the ſcope of the Apoſtle in theſe words (as appears by that Cauſal Particle, <hi>For</hi>) is only to preſs the foregoing Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it ſeems not reaſonable to abate the ſtrength of his Argument, by excluding the moſt perſwaſive Senſe of his words, and confining it (without neceſſity) to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of leſs concern, and weaker ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy, as moſt clearly that is which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects only the ſins of other men.</p>
               <p>But that which moſt ſtrongly confirms this to be the ſpecial Senſe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles words, is to be collected from the Connexion of this Verſe with the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wherein he forewarneth the Jewiſh Chriſtians, to whom the Epiſtle is directed,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43236:16"/>of a Fatal End that was near at hand: and thereupon adviſeth them, what they ſhould do to ſecure themſelves in that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>The end of all things is at hand, be ye therefore ſober, and watch unto prayer. And above all things have fervent Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty among your ſelves, for Charity will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a multitude of ſins.</hi> Whether by the end of all things be meant the End of the world, according to the common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, and that ſaid to be at hand in a certain Latitude of ſence, becauſe it was now the laſt time, the laſt hour, the laſt days, as was elſewhere frequently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by himſelf and his fellow Apoſtles, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.3. 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Jude</hi> 18. Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the laſt Age of the World, whereof, although the duration was not to be ſo ſhort, as might then be imagined from ſuch words as theſe: yet it was not to be long in the eyes of God, <hi>with whom a thouſand years are but as one day,</hi> as he advertiſeth them in his ſecond Epiſtle, Chap. 3.8. I ſay whether it be the <hi>end</hi> of the World, or (which is more probable to be the Apoſtles meaning) the Fatal Deſtruction of the obdurate Jews, their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43236:16"/>Politie Royal City, and Temple, foretold by Chriſt himſelf, and often ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by his Apoſtles, which was then very near indeed: This being the ground, and occaſion of the Apoſtles Exhortation to fervent Charity, leads us to the moſt reaſonable Interpretation of theſe latter words of the verſe: For <hi>Charity will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a multitude of ſins;</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That is, when the end of all things, which is near at hand, ſhall come, fervent Charity, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to, and joyned with Repentance, ſignified by the foregoing expreſſions of Sobriety, Watching and Praying, is the likelieſt means to propitiate the wrath of God, deſerved by a multitude of ſins, and to ſave you from the formidable judgement of God, which is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</q> I appeal to any indifferent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whether this coherence of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles words doth not determine his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to relate to the ſins of the Charitable Perſon, much rather than the ſins of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For although it be no leſs true, that the ſame Vertue of Charity will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a multitude of ſins in other men, in ſuch a ſence as ſhall be declared after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: yet how that ſhould be referred,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43236:17"/>(as by the Context in this place it is) to the end of all things: That is, how Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhould cover a multitude of ſins in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſons, when the end of all things is come, is hard to conceive; but eaſie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to underſtand, how it may then co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a multitude of ſins in the Charitable Perſon, as ſhall be ſhewed in its due place.</p>
               <p>The moſt rational Objection againſt this Interpretation and Argument for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the other Senſe, is raiſed from a parallel Text, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Hatred ſtirreth up ſtrife; but Love covereth all ſins.</hi> And if the Apoſtles words, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be borrowed from that Sentence, muſt receive the ſame Interpretation with that, it muſt neceſſarily be underſtood of other mens ſins; by the two contrary ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Love and Hatred, ſet forth in that Text, the one ſtirring up ſtrife, the other preventing it, by covering the faults of other men, by not taking notice of them, or looking favourably upon them, in order to a peaceable and friendly living with them</p>
               <p>But to this Objection it may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. 1. That it is not evident that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> did intend any quotation of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43236:17"/>there being no ſuch intimation in the Apoſtles words, as uſually there is, when any Text of the Old Teſtament is cited in the New, by thoſe words, <hi>as it is written,</hi> or other like, not found in this place. But to this Objection, together with ſome others, a fuller anſwer ſhall be made afterward.</p>
               <p>§. 2. The probability of this Senſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus declared from the Context, the Truth of it remains to be further confirmed from many other Texts of Scripture: but I ſuſpend the addition of them, till I have anſwered the ſecond Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the ſins ſpoken of in this Sentence to be the ſins of the Charitable perſon, the queſtion is, what's meant by the word Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, or in what Senſe they may be ſaid to be covered by Charity? The Anſwer to this Queſtion is to be collected from the ordinary uſe of the ſame Phraſe in other places of Scripture; wherein it is frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed to expreſs the pardon or forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſin, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.7. quoting <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1. <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, and whoſe ſins are covered.</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.2. <hi>Thou haſt forgiven the iniquity of thy People, thou haſt covered all their ſins.</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:43236:18"/>In theſe Texts, I ſuppoſe, no doubt can b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> made, but that the Covering of ſin ſigni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fies the ſame thing with the Forgiving. So <hi>Neh.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Cover not their iniquities, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> let not their ſin be blotted out, i. e.</hi> let i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not be forgiven. And becauſe Covering a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing is one way of hiding, therefore ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tranſlators have rendred the ſame Greek word uſed in another Text of like ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by the word Hiding.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.20. <hi>He which converteth a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from the error of his way, ſhall ſave a Soul from death, and ſhall hide a multitudes of ſins, i. e.</hi> ſhall procure the Pardon of them (as the words are commonly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted) or ſhall obtain the Forgiveneſs of a multitude of ſins in himſelf, as the learned <hi>Grotius</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> interpret them, agreeable to the fore-given ſenſe of the ſame Words in our Text. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of a ſinner from the errour of his Way is an eminent act of Charity, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it is induſtriouſly ſought and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, whatever the ſucceſs be. Nor is there any appearance of Incongruity, to ſay or ſuppoſe, that to endeavour the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an other man, and thereby to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Pardon of his ſins, ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43236:18"/>towards the obtaining of a pardon of ſins in the charitable Procurer. For if that Senſe, which I have given of the words of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> be admitted to import a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Truth, (as I doubt not to evince from many other Texts afterward) the like Senſe of this of St. <hi>James</hi> (whether by him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended or not) will neceſſarily follow to contain the ſame Truth. The Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a ſinner, or the ſincere and earneſt Endeavour thereof, being (as before was ſaid) an eminent act of Spiritual Charity. But for the probability of that Senſe of St. <hi>James</hi> his words, I muſt at this time refer the Reader to the Notes of the forenamed Doctor upon the Text, becauſe it would be too great an Excurſion to undertake the Confirming of it in this place. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be the true Senſe of St. <hi>James</hi> or not, no doubt can be made, but that the particular Phraſe of Covering of ſins doth very fitly expreſs the Pardon of them, when it is attributed to God, as in the Texts ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before: And when it is attributed to Men, or to any act or vertue in them, as it is in this Text, it may very fitly ſignifie the obtaining or procuring of ſuch a favour (as the Pardon of ſin) from God.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:43236:19"/>
               <p>The Metaphor may be borrowed from the Covering of Nakedneſs, to which ſin is often compared, or to the Covering of a Sore with a Plaiſter, or the Covering of a Debt charged in a Book, by way of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration or Blotting out, which is another Synonymous phraſe, ſignifying the Pardon of ſin. Both Phraſes ſignifying the Pardon thing with the Hiding of ſin from the face or the eyes of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.9. <hi>Hide thy face from my ſins, and blot out mine iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> Not that God ſhould not ſee them, but that he ſhould not impute them, as the ſame Words are interpreted by the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1, 2 and by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.7, 8. <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven, and whoſe ſins are covered, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the man to whom the Lord will not impute ſin.</hi> As Men are ſaid to hide their own ſins, when they will not acknowledge them, nor admit themſelves chargeable with the imputation of them: So doth God co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſin, by his not imputing, or charging the guilt of it upon a man. And this is one way amongſt others (as ſhall be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after declared) whereby Charity, or the Charitable Perſon doth cover a multitude of ſins in his Neighbour, according to the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43236:19"/>other Senſe of the Text, that is, doth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give and excuſe them, and ſo cover them from his own eyes, either by not taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of them, or not imputing them to the Offender.</p>
               <p>But to diſcharge this Queſtion; If by the multitude of ſins ſpoken of in this Text, be underſtood the ſins of the Charitable Perſon, it is ſufficiently evident by the Uſe of the Phraſe, what the Covering of them meaneth, <hi>viz.</hi> nothing leſs than the Pardon or Remiſſion of the ſaid ſins.</p>
               <p>§. 3. But then for a clear underſtanding of this Effect, it will be neceſſary to enquire what may be underſtood by the Pardon of ſin? A Phraſe not ſo plain, but that it hath afforded matter of more Controverſie, than I am willing to take notice of in this Place: intending to diſcharge my ſelf and my Reader of all the puzzle of Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about the nature and ſignification of this eaſie Word, and take up with that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meaning, which is moſt agreeable to common Senſe and Vulgar apprehenſion: Namely, that by the Pardon or Remiſſion of ſin is meant a Diſcharge of the ſin from the puniſhment, or obligation to puniſhment; For that the Remiſſion of <hi>the Fault,</hi> without
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43236:20"/>the Remiſſion of <hi>the Guilt,</hi> which <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> and Others of his Order conteſt for, is to me a Riddle, a ſenſeleſs Notion, and the Effect of it a real Nullity. Not but that there may be a true and effectual Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of the fault, without an abſolute and total Remiſſion of all puniſhment, as ſhall be ſhewn hereafter. But then the Remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fault, is no more then the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the puniſhment, and no more of the Fault is remitted, then is of the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or the Fault is no otherwiſe remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted than the Puniſhment is. But to imagin a Fault to be entirely or perfectly remitted, without any Remiſſion of the Puniſhment, is either a perfect Contradiction, or a very uncomfortable ſort of Pardon, and ſuch as I think, the Devils would not much envy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of Mankind to obtain.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore take it for granted, that all Pardon of ſin doth import ſome Remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at leaſt of the puniſhment, I ſay ſome Remiſſion, becauſe, as there is a great Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation in the nature, kinds, degrees, extent and duration of the Puniſhment; ſo may there be an anſwerable Variation and Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the Pardon of ſins, (ſignified by the phraſe of Covering of them in the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43236:20"/>Text) as to the matter, meaſures, degrees, and duration thereof. And ſo Sin may be truly ſaid to be covered or pardoned, not only when all the Puniſhment is remitted or removed, but alſo when any ſort, part or degree thereof is taken off or abated; as alſo when the remainder of Puniſhment is relieved, or balanced by ſome advantages to the Patient. But of this more is to be ſaid in the following Diſcourſe, concerning the Puniſhment of ſin in general.</p>
               <p>§. 4 The puniſhment of Sin, importing all evil conſequences thereof, is as various as the ſin, both in its kind and degrees. And as in the general Notion, all ſin doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in ſome repugnancy or oppoſition to the Will of God:
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.4.</note> So all Puniſhment conſiſts in ſomething that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the reaſonable will and wellfare of the Sinner. And this is moſt juſt, that he that will not obey the Will of God, ſhould be croſs'd in his own Will; if Men be ſo willfull, as not to ſubmit to the Will of God, they ſhall never have their own will, do what they can. For the natural and neceſſary Object of mans Will is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs then a true and real Happineſs, conſiſting in a perfect freedom from Evil,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43236:21"/>and in the injoyment of all the Good that he is capable of. But the only Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for this Happineſs is Holineſs, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the Conformity of our wills to the Will of God. He therefore that is not, at leaſt in ſome meaſure Holy, can never be in any meaſure Happy. But to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly or perfectly Happy, no man is, or can be capable, till he be perfectly Holy; that is, till there be a perfect Conformity of his will to the Will of God. There is no way to obtain a full and perfect Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to our own wills, but by ſubmitting them to the Will of God. So ſhall we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly at laſt have our own will, and fill of Happineſs: though for the preſent we do miſs of our own carnal and fooliſh will, and muſt ſtay for the accompliſhment of our moſt reaſonable Deſires, till we be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of it. The true, ſubſtantial, final, and perfect Object of our will, (ſuppoſing that it be conformable and obedient to the Will of God) we cannot fail of at laſt; but muſt not look for it, till we come where it is to be had, that is, in Heaven, (for Earth is not capable of it) where all our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, unſatisfying Volitions, Wiſhes and Deſires will be utterly extinct, and our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43236:21"/>whole will and affections will be ſatisfied with the utmoſt Felicity they are capable of: So that we ſhall have nothing further to wiſh, but the unchangeable Continuance of that State; And that alſo we ſhall be ſo well aſſured of, as that the Will, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in that reſpect ſhall be abundantly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. Whence one hath fitly called Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs <hi>Pax Deſiderii, a rest or peace to all Deſire.</hi> When Deſire ſhall give place to Joy, and ſtir no more, whereas here it is reſtleſs, and never can ceaſe, till it be fully ſatisfied.</p>
               <p>But to return from this digreſſion, to the Diſcourſe that occaſion'd it. I ſaid before, that all ſin is a tranſgreſſion, or oppoſition to the will of God, and all puniſhment conſiſts in ſomething oppoſite to the reaſonable Object of our own wills. But here it is to be noted, that as men may be miſtaken in the Object of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Will, thinking that to be agreeable, which is contrary thereunto: So may they be deceived in the right Object of their own wills, which in the true Notion is ſomething that is good for them, and tending to their ſafety, welfare, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. But this apprehenſion is very li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43236:22"/>to errour, and nothing more common then for men by ſuch errour, <hi>to call evil good, and good evil, to put darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs, to put bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter,</hi> as in things that relate to the Will of God, ſo in things relating to the right Objects of their own will, and happineſs. But this errour cannot change the nature of the things in either caſe. The bare thinking of a thing to be good, or evil, doth not make it ſo, either in a Moral, or in a Phyſical ſenſe: Men may be puniſhed in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of their own blind and infatuate wills: and they may be bleſſed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded in the want of ſuch enjoyments, and in things contrary thereunto. A re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted good, though it gratifies the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived will, may be a real puniſhment; and a ſenſible evil ſuffered againſt a mans will, may be a ſignal Bleſſing: To be puniſhed by Proſperity, and bleſſed by Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, is no contradiction. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was hardned to his deſtruction, by the ceſſation of the Plagues; and <hi>Manaſſes</hi> was ſaved by his Captivity, and the Fetters of his Priſon. And many a man may ſay, <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riiſſem, niſi periiſſem,</hi> I had periſhed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43236:22"/>if I had not been undone for a time.</p>
               <p>It is not neceſſary to the puniſhment of ſin, that men ſhould be at the preſent ſenſible of it. And though he muſt needs be unhappy for the preſent, that thinks himſelf ſo, becauſe that thought is enough to make him ſo, as being inconſiſtent with his preſent happineſs: yet he is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily happy that accounts himſelf ſo: otherwiſe men might be happy when they are out of their wits: and made miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in recovering them. As the man in the Poet complained.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Pol me occidiſtis amici</l>
                  <l>Non ſervâſtis, ait, cui ſic extorta voluptas,</l>
                  <l>Et demptus per vim mentis gratiſſimus error.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Horat. Epiſt. 2. Lib. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p>But to hold to the Analogy between the Will of God, and the will of Man, in the nature of ſin and puniſhment, I ſay further, that as the Will of God is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed by omiſſion, or commiſſion, by leaving undone ſomething which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, or doing ſomething which he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids: ſo the puniſhments of ſin are either <hi>Privative,</hi> or <hi>Poſitive,</hi> conſiſting in the loſs, or want of ſomething that is Good
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43236:23"/>and Deſirable by a reaſonable Will, or in the ſenſe and ſuffering of ſomething which is Evil and grievous to the Will. And both theſe ſorts of Puniſhments, are ſuch as befall Men in this Life, or in that which is to come, and ſo are temporal, or Eternal: Some of them alſo are <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> and <hi>neceſſary,</hi> and ſome <hi>contingent</hi> and <hi>avoidable,</hi> as being ordered and appointed by the juſt Will and Providence of God, without any natural or abſolute Neceſſity of their Event. I ſay, ſome ſorts of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſin are <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> as being the Natural Effects and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents of the ſin, and ſo, neceſſary and unavoidable, and that either abſolutely, or without a Miracle. Abſolutely una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable the Puniſhment muſt needs be, when the Separation of the Penal Event imports contradiction to the ſinfull act, as is evident, not only in the caſe of Self-mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (which being nothing elſe but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving a man of his Life, cannot without Contradiction be ſeparated from the priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Puniſhment) but alſo in all other ſins, whereby Men do deprive themſelves, at leaſt for the preſent, of the enjoyment of Health, Honour, Friends, or any other
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43236:23"/>good thing. And as every act of true Vertue doth in a juſt ſenſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it ſelf by its real and moral Goodneſs;
<note place="margin">Virius eſt ſui ipſius merces.</note> ſo doth every ſinfull Act puniſh it ſelf by its turpitude or evil deformity, which in the School Language is called the <hi>Macula,</hi> or ſtain of ſin And this Puniſhment is in the nature of the thing inſeparable from the ſin. Other puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are not ſo abſolutely neceſſary, as to imply any Contradiction in the avoidance or evaſion of them, and yet are really unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable without a Miracle, as is obvious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to conceive without any Inſtances.</p>
               <p>Now in ſuch caſes the covering of the ſin, as it ſignifies a total Remiſſion, or perfect Exemption from all Puniſhment, is either ſimply unpoſſible, as in the caſe of ſuch abſolute neceſſity of the Event, as implies a contradiction to the ſin in the avoidance, or elſe is not promiſed, or to be expected (though poſſible by Miracle) upon any condition. I ſay ſuch a cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſin as imports a total Remiſſion of Puniſhment, is either impoſſible, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectable: Yet may the ſame ſin in ſome other ſence be many ways covered, <hi>viz.</hi> by abatement of the degrees of the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43236:24"/>which is not wholly avoidable; or by deliverance from ſome other Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, which might be added in this Life, and that which is to come: or by ſundry manner and meaſures of Support, Relief, and Comfort in the Suffering, or by other ways, whereby the Puniſhment may be converted to the Advantage of the Sufferer, eſpecially in his Spiritual E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; which Advantages are ſo far from being inconſiſtent with the nature of a Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, that they are ordinarily deſigned, as the main end of it, both by God and Man, as in all caſtigatory Puniſhments; whence God is ſaid to chaſten us for our Profit, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10. And a Puniſhment ceaſeth not to be ſo, by being converted to a Bleſſing. Thus may the ſins of a Charitable Perſon be covered, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny abſolute Remiſſion, or Exemption from Puniſhment, which may be in it ſelf ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. And where it is not ſo, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent at the Will and Providence of God; it is more eaſie to conceive how the ſin may be covered by Suſpenſion, or Remiſſion of Puniſhment, in whole, or in part.</p>
               <p>Here a queſtion may be moved, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:43236:24"/>How far that Remiſſion of ſin, which is ſignified by the Term of covering in this Text, may be expected to extend? <hi>i. e.</hi> Whether only to the Temporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which a ſinner is liable to in this Life, or to that alſo which is to come in another World?</p>
               <p>Towards a full Anſwer to this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, it will not be amiſs to reflect upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he words of the Apoſtle immediately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding the Text which I am treating up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein I conceive a convenient hint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s offered, for the Reſolution of this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, from a double Interpretation which is given of thoſe words <hi>(the end of all things is at hand.)</hi> the one relating to this Life, the other to that which is to come.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some Modern Interpreters of Good Note for their Learning and Judgement,
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> Mr. <hi>Joſ. Mede,</hi> and others.</note> do underſtand thoſe words, not to be meant of the end of the World, or the day of Judgement, but of the end of the Jewiſh Common-wealth, by the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Temple, and the City of Jeruſalem, together with the General Calamity of that People by their Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:43236:25"/>and Diſperſion throughout the World, by the Power and Victory of the <hi>Romans,</hi> often foretold by our Saviour, and called <hi>the abomination of deſolation:</hi> For the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding of which Calamity, the Apoſtle adviſeth the Chriſtian Jews, to whom he directs this Epiſtle, <hi>to be ſober, and to watch unto prayer,</hi> as hopefull means to ſave them from the extremity of that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity: Adding further, in this verſe, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſpecial Point of advice to the ſame end, to wit, <hi>the exerciſe of a fervent Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> If this ſenſe of the Apoſtles words be allowed, ſuppoſing the end of all things ſo near approaching, as was the time of that Publick Calamity (which ſenſe by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Interpreters is alſo applied to many other Texts of our Saviours and the Apoſtles ſpeaking of the end of the World, as very near) I ſay, if this be the Apoſtles Senſe in this place, no doubt can be made of this effect of Charity, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Deliverance from Puniſhments of ſin in this Life.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, If by <hi>the end of all things</hi> muſt be underſtood that General End which is to come at the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to the more ordinary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43236:25"/>of the words, it is evident, that this benefit of Charity will extend to another Life. But becauſe the Puniſhment of ſin (as hath been ſaid before) is both in this Life, and that which is to come, without Determining the true Senſe of the foregoing Verſe, I doubt not to conclude, that the Remiſſion of ſin, expreſſed by the covering thereof, declared by the Apoſtle, is not to be limited to this or the other Life, but may be underſtood of both, and will be verified either in both, or at leaſt in one of theſe two Lives; that is where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever this Vertue of Charity is found, it will be available by the Mercy of God at leaſt to ſome kind of Remiſſion of ſin, <hi>i. e.</hi> of the Puniſhment thereof, either in this Life, and that which is to come too, or elſe in one of them more or leſs, according to the ſincerity and degree of the Charity.</p>
               <p>If the Charity be the Fruit of an unfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Faith accompanied with Repentance, (as it muſt needs be, if it be ſincere) it will undoubtedly be available to the Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſin in the other World, if not alſo to the Remiſſion of Puniſhment in this World; which is very hopefull, though not ſo certain in all Reſpects, as is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43236:26"/>of future Puniſhment in the Life to come: Becauſe there are ſome ſorts of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments of ſin in this Life, which (as was ſhewed before) are in themſelves neceſſary, and inſeparable Conſequents of the ſin, and ſo unavoidable in their Nature, as Shame and Diſhonour in ſins known to the World, privation of Benefits conſequent to other ſins, ſorrow and remorſe of Conſcience, common to all ſins, whereof a ſinner is convinced: Beſides ſome other ſorts of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments in this Life, not ſo neceſſary in their kind, may be conſequent to the ſin, by the Juſtice and Wiſdom, and alſo by the Goodneſs of God: which therefore he may refuſe to remit in this Life, where he intends a full Remiſſion in the Life to come. This is plain in the Caſe of <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. Many ſevere Puniſhments are threatned by <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, to be executed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>David</hi> for his ſcandalous ſins of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and Murder, which were never remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but punctually executed upon him, notwithſtanding, that upon his Repentance, teſtified by his humble Confeſſion, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet aſſures him, that <hi>God had put away his ſin,</hi> and <hi>that he ſhould not die.</hi> Ver. 13. <hi>And David ſaid unto Nathan, I have
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43236:26"/>ſinned againſt the Lord; and Nathan ſaid unto David, the Lord alſo hath put away thy ſin, thou ſhalt not die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His repentance expreſſed by extraordinary teſtimonies of his Sorrow and Humiliation, ſet forth in that <hi>Pſalm,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> which was penn'd and publiſhed by himſelf for that end, was not ſufficient to deliver him from all Puniſhment of his ſin, although it was accepted for his Deliverance, not only from the puniſhment of eternal Death, but alſo of ſuch a temporal Death, as he was juſtly lyable to by the Law; which though it could not be executed upon him by any Human Authority, by reaſon of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, yet might have been executed by the Hand of God, who had threatned by Himſelf to revenge and puniſh ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſins, as the Magiſtrate could not, or ſhould neglect to puniſh, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.14. But did not thereby deprive himſelf of liberty to forbear ſuch Execution of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment according to his Wiſdom and Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>By this Example, and ſeveral others that might be alledged (if it were needfull in this place) it appears, that a Part of the puniſhment of ſin may be remitted, where
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43236:27"/>the whole is not, which I take to be the common Caſe of Mankind, fallen under the guilt and puniſhment of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin; for it is experimentally evident,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> that the whole Puniſhment is not remitted to any Man, becauſe all are known to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer many Penalties threatned in this Life, beſides that common one of Temporal Death; whilſt that of Eternal Death is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to many, and promiſed to all that repent.</p>
               <p>But to return to the Point in hand, I ſay, ſincere Charity proceeding from a true Faith, and accompanied with an unfeigned Repentance, will certainly deliver the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Perſon from the Everlaſting puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of another Life, and may alſo be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable either to ſave a man from all Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments in this Life, or to abate the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of them.</p>
               <p>But if the Charity be not fincere, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with any ſuch Repentance, as will render the ſinner capable of Salvation in the other Life, yet it may be, and doubtleſs will be available for the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the perſon from Puniſhments in this Life, either in whole or in part. For as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther temporal Rewards are given by God to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:43236:27"/>partial and infincere Vertues, and good Works, ſo may this of Deliverance from temporal Judgments. And this perhaps was ſometimes the only meaning of thoſe words of our Saviour, recorded in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, to have been ſpoken to divers Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that came to him to be healed of their bodily Diſeaſes, expreſſing thereby ſome kind of Faith in him, and his Power. And he ſaid unto them, <hi>thy ſins are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given thee, i. e.</hi> the Puniſhment of thy ſins which lies upon thee is taken off, and remitted,
<note place="margin">Mark 3.34. cap. 10.52. Luke 7.50. cap. 8.48. cap. 18.42.</note> and thou ſhalt be healed. Which ſeems to be the ſence of another Phraſe often uſed by our Saviour in like caſes to them that came to him, for the healing of their Diſeaſes. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.22. <hi>Thy faith hath ſaved thee, i. e.</hi> hath made thee whole, as 'tis there rendred in our Engliſh Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, agreeable to the following words, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>and the woman was made whole from that hour.</hi> Not that I ſuppoſe this to be all the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, that he ever intended to any Perſon, to whom he uttered thoſe words, (thy ſins are forgiven thee) amongſt whom, it is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:43236:28"/>more than probable, there were ſome, whoſe Faith did qualifie them for a better remiſſion of their ſin. But it is not evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that every one of thoſe Perſons, that were cured of their bodily Diſeaſes by him, were endued with ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Faith, as did render them capable of an abſolute Remiſſion of all their ſins, as to another Life: For to think as ſome Divines have ſaid, that our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our never cured the body of any Patient, but he cured their ſouls alſo, ſeems to be but an improbable opinion.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſing this Remiſſion of ſin, as relating only to Temporal Puniſhments in this Life, to be granted, as a Reward of an Inſincere Charity: the Queſtion may be moved, whether the like Charity, or any works thereof may not be available alſo to ſome degree of Remiſſion, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of ſin, in the Life to come, at the laſt Judgement?</p>
               <p>To this Queſtion I ſhall not preſume to anſwer dogmatically, as not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring at preſent any particular Teſtimony of Scripture, whereby that Queſtion may be determined, either in the Negative, or Affirmative: notwithſtanding my Opinion
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43236:28"/>inclines to the Affirmative, <hi>viz.</hi> that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſuch an infincere Charity can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail nothing towards a total Remiſſion at the laſt Judgement, or the Salvation of the Perſon; whereof no man can be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, whithout an unfeigned Repentance, and ſuch a true Faith as works by ſincere Love to God and his Neighbour yet that even ſuch Good Works, as do indeed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from Charity, and are not done hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritically, for ſelf Intereſt, Worldly ends, or carnal Motives only, may abate the Degrees of the future Puniſhment in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Life.</p>
               <p>My reaſon for this Opinion is grounded upon that Fundamental Principle of all Religion; That all men ſhall fare in the life to come,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.10.</note> according to the things done by them in this Life, whether they be good, or whether they be bad. Which Rule is underſtood not only of the reſpective ſtates of Salvation, and Damnation, but alſo of the degrees of Reward and Puniſhment in that ſtate. As for the ſtate of Puniſhment, no queſtion hath been, or can be made, concerning the difference of its degrees, expreſsly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in Scripture, ſignifying that it ſhall
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:43236:29"/>be more tolerable for ſome,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.15. chap. 11.22. Luke 12.47, 48.</note> than for others in that day; wherein ſome ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes, and ſome with fewer. And the Queſtion that is made about the degrees of Glory, is but a novel one, none of the Ancients (that I know of) and very few Modern Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines have embraced the Opinion, that aſſerts the equality of that ſtate.</p>
               <p>The Catholick Doctrine founded upon Scripture ſuppoſes as much diſparity of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Glory and Happineſs in Heaven, as of Puniſhment in Hell, and that the reſpective meaſures of each condition will be allotted and aſſigned, according to ſuch proportion of Good and Evil, as upon an exact and infallible Evidence before an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Judge, ſhall be found in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be judged, with Relation to the bodily Life paſt So is that Judgement deſcribed by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John,</hi> Rev. 20.12. <hi>And I ſaw the dead, both ſmall and great, ſtand before God, and the Books were opened, and another Book was opened, which is the Book of Life, and the dead were judged out of thoſe things, which were written in the Books, according to their Works.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:43236:29"/>
               <p>And that among all ſorts of Good Works, thoſe of Charity to our Brethren will then have a ſpecial Confideration, is ſufficiently intimated by the words of our Saviour in his own Deſcription of the laſt Judgement. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31. to the end of the Chapter, <hi>I was an hungred, and ye gave me meat, I was thirſty, and ye gave me drink, I was a ſtranger, and ye took me in, naked, and ye clothed me,</hi> &amp;c, A Text which I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak more largely of afterward, in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this Doctrine. And as by this Declaration of our Saviour himſelf, who is to be Judge at that day, it is evident, that Works of Charity, proceeding from an unfeigned Faith, will then be ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered, as a qualification for the General Reward; ſo that the Degrees and Meaſures of that Reward, will be propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd to the Meaſures of Charity, ſeems no leſs evident by the words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, ſpeaking alſo of the ſame ſort of works, 2. Cor. 9.6. <hi>He which ſoweth ſparingly ſhall reap ſparingly, and he which ſoweth bountifully, ſhall reap bountifully.</hi> And in the words of our Saviour, in the forementioned Text, it is likewiſe added,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:43236:30"/>as a Reaſon of the Sentence of Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to be denounced againſt them on the left hand, verſe 41. <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels, For I was an hungred, and ye gave me no meit, I was thirſty, and ye gave me no drink,</hi> &amp;c. Signifying, that one juſt cauſe of that juſt Sentence, will be the neglect of this great Duty of Charity; whence it will follow, upon a reaſonable account, that look how much that ſin of neglect, or omiſſion ſhall be found to be abated, by any thing done by the Perſon to be judged, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for that fault, ſo much will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated of the Puniſhment; And though ſome Works of Charity, bearing no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the ability of him that doth them, may be reckon'd as none, in the Senſe of our Saviours words, and in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to a mans diſcharge from the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Sentence; yet it cannot be ſaid, that he that hath done ſome Works of Charity, is altogether ſo guilty of the omiſſion of that Duty, as he that hath done none: And conſequently, cannot be equally liable upon that account to the ſame degrees of Puniſhment: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:43236:30"/>his Charity, how defective ſoever it was, will ſave him from ſome degrees of Puniſhment in that ſtate: Beſides all the validity it had to exempt him from Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, and to procure any Temporal Reward in this Life.</p>
               <p>What other Conſideration may be had, by the Judge at that day of Works of Charity done by any Perſon, that then ſhall be found <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Reprobate</hi> (and ſo fall into condemnation) towards any counterpoiſe of his other ſins, or of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement of the degrees of their Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I cannot tell. But this is certain, that what ever can be equitably plended for the abatement of Puniſhment, will be conſidered by that Judge, who is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely Wiſe and Juſt, knowing exactly the Merits and Circumſtances of every mans caſe, that is to be tryed before him; and who will be Advocate, as well as Judge, for every ſinner, as far as his caſe will bear. And therefore, as in humane Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, or Exerciſe of diſtributive Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice amongſt men, when a Criminal is to be judged, although his caſe be ſuch, as can neither admit of a Juſtification, nor yet of a Plenary Pardon, yet it is thought
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:43236:31"/>no more than reaſonable, that ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration ſhould be had of the reſt of his Life, eſpecially, if there be any Good E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of any Special Laudable Actions done by him, they may be conſidered, toward the abatement of utmoſt ſeverity in the Penalty, where any ſuch abute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is poſſible, as in Puniſhments which are not Capital: So, (though I cannot aſſure any man, that it ſhall be ſo, in the caſe of any Perſons falling under the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Sentence of Condemnation, yet) I think there is ſome Reaſon to hope, that he that hath ſhewed Mercy to Men in this Life, though he be not ſaved, may find ſome Mercy in the degrees of his Puniſhment; And that not only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of ſuch an abatement of his Guilt, as was before ſignified reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſins of omiſſion, but alſo with reſpect to his ſins of commiſſion. That there will be ſome kind of Counterpoiſe, or Ballance of Good and Evil Works in the Divine Judgement, and execution of Juſtice, is not (in my opinion) to be rejected as a meer Rabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical or Platonical con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe, qui ne contre poiſe.</hi> Is the French Prov.</note> though it be ſo too,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:43236:31"/>but ſeems to be in ſome meaſure probable, as it is agreeable to the nature of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, exerciſed amongſt men, privately and publickly.</p>
               <p>The Summ of what I have ſaid in the Explication of that Senſe of the Apoſtles words, which I here maintain, is this: That Charity if it be ſincere as the Fruit of an unfeighed Faith and Repentance, will be available towards a plenary Covering or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of a mans ſins, at the laſt Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; If it be not ſo, yet it will procure him ſome Remiſſion at leaſt, if not Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption from temporal Puniſhment in this Life, (beſides other poſitive Rewards, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily given to the practice of this Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue) and may alſo be available towards the Abatement of the Degrees of poſitive Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment in the Life to come. I ſay, of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Puniſhment,</hi> commonly called <hi>Paena Sensûs, Pain or Puniſhment of Senſe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>the Privative Puniſhment, Poena Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> the Puniſhment of Loſs, can admit of no degrees of Abatement: For <hi>the loſs of Eternal Life</hi> will be equal to all that are not ſaved, and can be no other from the Nature of the thing, though the ſenſe and affliction of that Loſs may differ much,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:43236:32"/>according to the different capacities Men were in to obtain that Life, and the inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Means thereof received, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected or neglected. For in this reſpect the Loſs of Eternal Life will be more tolerable (as our Saviour ſaith) for <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah,</hi> for <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> that never had the like means of Salvation (though they were not excluded from all means or poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility thereof) then it will be for <hi>Bethſaida</hi> or <hi>Capernaum.</hi> And ſo it will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably, for all People under like Ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality of the means of Life; neither is it poſſible for any Perſon, that never had any ſuch Means, as ſome other had, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be guilty of Rejecting or Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting them, I ſay, it is not poſſible for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch Perſon to fall under the ſame De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of that neceſſary Puniſhment of the never-dying Worm, as that is ſuppoſed to ſignifie, the anguiſh and torment of the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Conſcience. This natural puniſhment of the Afflicted, or afflicting Conſcience, for the ſame Reaſon muſt needs be abated alſo to him, that hath done ſome Good works of Charity in this Life, becauſe his Conſcience cannot charge him, at the ſame rate, as it muſt needs do him, that hath
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:43236:32"/>totally neglected them, under an equal or larger Ability.</p>
               <p>Whether the ſubſtance of this Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Text, either neceſſary or moſt probable, muſt be left to the judgment of the Reader, but that it is neither Popiſh, nor Singular (as ſome may be ready to charge it) I muſt take leave to challenge, whiles I find that this Senſe of the Words hath neither been received by all Papiſts, nor rejected by all Proteſtants: Some of the Pontificians baulking this Interpretation,
<note place="margin">as <hi>Eſtius, Tiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and others.</note> which I inſiſt upon, do give the ſame, which is given by moſt Proteſtants, namely, That Charity will cover the ſins of other Men (not the ſins of the Charitable Perſon) in ſuch a Senſe as is hereafter to be declared. And ſome Eminent Proteſtants do admit that other Senſe, which I prefer, as moſt probable. And that not only in this Text, but alſo in that of St. <hi>James,</hi> wherein the ſame Phraſe is uſed, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.20. <hi>He which converteth a ſinner from the Errour of his ways, ſhall ſave a Soul from Death, and ſhall hide a Multitude of ſins.</hi> The origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Words are the ſame in both Texts, and are thus Paraphraſed by a Learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:43236:33"/>of our own Church.
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Hammond.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">It is a moſt excellent glorious Work, which he hath wrought, the Effect of which is, that God will free him, on whom this Change is wrought, from Death eternal, and perhaps, from preſent temporal Death, through Sickneſs fallen upon him for that ſin, <hi>vid.</hi> v. 15. And beſides he will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and reward the Charity of him that hath wrought that good Work, with the free Diſcharge of whatſoever ſins he hath formerly been guilty of, but hath now repented of.</q> See the ſame Authors An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notation upon the Text. This Senſe is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the words of the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, Dan.</hi> 12.3. <hi>They that turn many to Righteouſneſs, ſhall ſhine as the Stars for ever, viz.</hi> in Heavenly Glory, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily implyes a Remiſſion of their ſins. And why the zealous Endeavouring to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert ſinners from the Error, <hi>i. e.</hi> evil of their Way ſhould be available to procure the Covering of a multitude of ſins, in him that makes it his care and ſtudy ſo to do, a very good Reaſon may be given from the nature of the Act, which imports one of the beſt Teſtimonies of Repentance that can be. In that Penetential Pſalm, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:43236:33"/>
                  <hi>David</hi> ſues to Almighty God, for the Pardon of his groſs ſins of Murder and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, he urges this as a Motive towards the obtaining of his Requeſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Then will I teach Tranſgreſſors thy Ways, and ſinners ſhall be converted unto Thee.</hi> And ſurely no greater Reparation can be made by ſinfull man to Almighty God for the diſhonour done to his Majeſty by his own ſins; than when the penitent ſinner, together with his own Hearty repentance and amendment of Life, ſhall endeavour alſo, as much as lies in his power, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of other ſinners unto God. So did <hi>Abner</hi> deſign to make his peace with King <hi>David,</hi> after his profeſſed Enmity and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion firſt by Promiſing to ſerve him for the time to come in his own Perſon, and then to bring over all <hi>Iſrael</hi> with him to the Obedience of the King, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.10.</p>
               <p>And that the Practice of this great ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Charity, in other Inſtances, as well as this of endeavouring to Convert ſinners from their evil Ways, is the beſt Means of Satisfaction to God, or appeaſing his Wrath for ſin, may appear by theſe two Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is in it ſelf moſt pleaſing
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:43236:34"/>and acceptable to Him, as moſt agreeable to his own Goodneſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe it tends to the procuring of much Glory to his Name, as otherwiſe, ſo <hi>by the Thankſgiving of many</hi> (engaged by the Benefit of Charity extended to them) <hi>redounding to the Glory of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.11. &amp; 4.15.</p>
               <p>If a Man hath incurred the juſt Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of any Man, what better means can be uſed to recover his Favour, than by doing of ſuch things, as he knows to be moſt pleaſing and acceptable to him; or if he hath any way Diſhonoured him, what bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Satisfaction can be done him, towards the repairing of that Injury, than by Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to promote his Honour effectually ſome other way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>HAving thus ſufficiently illuſtrated that Senſe of the Text, which ſeemeth to me moſt probable, I am ſenſible of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a further Confirmation thereof. Wherein I think this Demand ſhould not be denied me by any Indifferent Judge;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:43236:34"/>namely; That if the Doctrine collected from this Interpretation, be proved to be True; and ſufficiently Confirmable from other Scriptures, this Interpretation hath a fair advantage of Preference before the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from the before noted Scope of the Context, and the far greater Validity of the Argument thus underſtood, to enforce the Exhortation that precedes it. And therefore towards the better ſatisfaction of ſome prejudiced Readers (whoſe Objections ſhall be conſidered in due place) it will be neceſſary to ſhew the undeniable Truth of this Doctrine, from other Texts of both Teſtaments, which for their Number are far more than are abſolutely neceſſary for the Confirmation of any Doctrine. Nor ſhould I think it reaſonable to quote ſo many of them, as I ſhall do, were it not, that by the ſame Labour, I hope, not only to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the Truth of this Doctrine, but alſo to promote the Practice of the Apoſtles Exhortation upon this ſingular Motive, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to many others, which fall not within the compaſs of this Text. I ſay, that by the many Texts (by which I hope to make it appear, that Charity to our Neighbours for Gods ſake, and with reſpect to his Will
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:43236:35"/>and good Pleaſure, is ſo much conducible to the Pardon of our ſins,) the Practice of this Vertue, will alſo appear more adviſable to them, that are leaſt diſpoſed to it, than perhaps hath been formerly conſidered or underſtood by them. And whereas moſt of the Texts, which I ſhall alledge to this Purpoſe, do ſeem to ſpeak of a full and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Remiſſion of all ſins at the Day of Judgment I ſuppoſe it will be eaſily yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Argument from the Greater to the Leſs, that if Charity be available for Deliverance from the Eternal puniſhment of the Life to come, it may well be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, it may alſo avail for a Redemption from Temporal puniſhments in this Life, (which are juſtly to be feared) or for an Abatement.</p>
               <p>The firſt Argument which I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce for the Truth of this Doctrine, ſhall be taken from thoſe Texts, which ſpeak of ſuch an Act of Charity, as is more commonly underſtood in this Text; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That whereby we Cover the ſins of others, by Forgiving them their Treſpaſſes againſt our ſelves. And the expreſs words of our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.14, 15. are, that <hi>if ye forgive men their Treſpaſſes, your
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:43236:35"/>Heavenly Father will alſo forgive you: but if ye forgive not Men their Treſpaſſes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will your Heavenly Father forgive you.</hi> By which Text it appears plainly, that the Truth of that Senſe of St. <hi>Peters</hi> words, which I plead for, is no other then a juſt Conſequence of the other, more common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received. That if it be true, that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity will cover a Multitude of ſins in other Men, it will alſo procure the ſame Effect to the Charitable Perſon, that is, cover a Multitude of ſins in him, he that forgives ſhall be forgiven. And in another Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt we find our Saviour expreſly directing us to this Work of Charity for the ſame End, namely, that our ſins may be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.25. <hi>When ye ſtand praying, forgive, if ye have ought againſt any, that your Father which is in Heaven may forgive you your Treſpaſſes: But if you do not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, neither will your Father which is in Heaven forgive your Treſpaſſes.</hi> That which our Saviour himſelf directs us to do for this End, may it not be done by us to that End? And is it not confidently to be believed to be Effectual and Available thereunto? And is not the ſame Effect as manifeſtly implyed in that Prayer which
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:43236:36"/>our Saviour hath taught us? <hi>Forgive us our Debts,</hi> i. e. our ſins, <hi>as we forgive our Debters, i. e.</hi> them that treſpaſs againſt us, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.4. Where the Particles <hi>As,</hi> in the one Evangeliſt, and <hi>For,</hi> in the other, do ſignifie the ſame thing, namely, A Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive uſed by our Saviours direction to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Effect of our Petition, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by an expreſs Promiſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.37. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, and ye ſhall be forgiven.</hi> Add to this from the beginning of the ſame Sermon of our Bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Bleſſed are the Mercifull, for they ſhall obtain Mercy,</hi> and as Mercy in us is a Branch of Charity; ſo the Covering or Pardon of ſins is an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Part of that Mercy that is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained thereby. Theſe Sentences of our Bleſſed Saviour, together with divers others to the ſame Purpoſe, I ſuppoſe might be alluded to by St. <hi>James</hi> in that Saying, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.13. <hi>For he ſhall have Judgement without Mercy, that hath ſhewed no Mercy, and Mercy rejoyceth againſt Judgement.</hi> Mercy in the Text comprehends all works of Charity, as well in the latter as in the former Clauſe. They that would have the latter Clauſe to be underſtood only of the Mercy of God triumphing over his Juſtice,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:43236:36"/>ſeem not to conſider the Context, before and after theſe Words, which apparently ſpeaks of ſuch Mercy and Charity, as is to be exerciſed by Men toward their Brethren, which being alſo the undoubted Meaning of the Word in this Verſe; the plain ſenſe of the whole Verſe can be no other than this, that the Unmercifull man ſhall find no Mercy in the day of Judgment. On the contrary, that Mercy, or the Mercifull man, ſhall have his Judgment ſo tempered with Mercy, as to give him cauſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in that Day for Deliverance or Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from the Judgment of Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or the Fear of it. This Goodneſs or Mercy found in Men, (if it be true and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere) being the Effect of Gods Grace, doth diſpoſe and fit Men for Divine Mercy. Mercy in the Perſon to be judged qualifies him for the Mercy of the Judge. Not that any ſuch Charity or Mercy can be found in a Sinner, as is ſufficient in it ſelf to juſtifie him, or expiate his ſin in ſtrictneſs of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or Merit, but that by the Goodneſs and Mercy of God, for Chriſts Sake, it ſhall obtain this Effect in the laſt Judgment.</p>
               <p>And as in this firſt Branch of the Text, the word Mercy twice uſed doth plainly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:43236:37"/>the Mercy of God, as well as the mercy of Man; <hi>He ſhall have Judgment without Mercy, i. e.</hi> from God, <hi>that hath ſhewed no Mercy</hi> to men. So in the ſecond Branch, the ſame word Mercy, may have reſpect both to the Mercy of God (as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Good Divines have interpreted it) and to the Mercy of men. It is Mercy in God rejoycing over Judgment or Juſtice, that gives men Cauſe of Rejoycing; and Mercy in men, that by Divine Acceptance quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies them for that Mercy of God.</p>
               <p>This Sentence of St. <hi>James,</hi> in both Parts of it, ſtands fully confirmed by that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or Repreſentation of the laſt Judgment, which is given by our Saviour, <hi>Matt.</hi> 25. from the 21 ver. to the end of the 41 ver. <hi>Then ſhall he ſay to them on the Left hand, depart from me ye Curſed into Everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> There's Judgment with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Mercy, and the Reaſon of it follows, <hi>For I was an Hungred and ye Fed me not, I was Thirſty and ye gave me no Drink, Naked and ye Clothed me not, &amp;c. In as much as ye did it not to theſe little ones, ye did it not to me.</hi> That is, ye ſhewed no Mercy, for my Sake to them that needed
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:43236:37"/>it. So is the firſt Part of the Apoſtles Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence confirmed, and exemplified by the latter Part of our Saviours: <hi>They ſhall have Judgment without Mercy that ſhewed no Mercy.</hi> The ſecond Part of the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Sentence is likewiſe abundantly confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the firſt Part of our Saviours. <hi>Then ſhall the King ſay unto them on the Right hand, come ye Bleſſed of my Father, receive the Kingdom prepared for you from the Foundation of the World; For I was an Hungred and ye gave me Meat, I was Thirſty, and ye gave me Drink, &amp;c.</hi> That is, by his own Interpretation, ver. 40. <hi>In as much as ye have done it unto one of the leaſt of my Brethren</hi> (being alſo your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) <hi>you have done it unto me.</hi> Where 'tis to be noted, how the Mercifull Man hath not only his ſins covered, for which he might have been Condemned, but is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to a ſtate of Glory, and Triumph in the Kingdom of Heaven. So doth Mercy not only eſcape but triumph over Judgment.</p>
               <p>In each part of this Deſcription of the diſtributive Juſtice, or Judgement of God in the latter day, a common <hi>Synechdoche</hi> of the Part for the Whole, muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:43236:38"/>that is, in the Aſſignment of the reſpective Reaſons of the contrary Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Abſolution and Condemnation. For neither will Charity be reſpected as the only reaſon, or condition of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but therewith alſo all other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Vertues, and Good Works, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that of an unfeigned Faith, as the Root of them all. Nor will the want of Charity, or the Vices moſt contrary to it, be the only reaſon of the Sentence of Condemnation; but all other ſins againſt the known will of God, will be jointly reſpected in the awarded Puniſhment. But ſince it hath pleaſed our Saviour, who is himſelf to be Judge at that day, to ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie theſe two oppoſite Practiſes as the only Inſtances of the reaſon of his future Judgement, we have ſufficient ground to conclude, that they will be eſpecially, though not only, conſidered by him in that Judgement.</p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Synechdoche</hi> of the Part for the Whole, neceſſary to be underſtood in the words of our Saviour, which we have laſt mentioned, is no leſs neceſſary to be underſtood in all Promiſes of the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to any particular Vertue, or ſort of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:43236:38"/>Good Works, of any kind. Partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no ſingle Vertue, that is ſincere and genuine, can exiſt without a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of all other Vertues, as hath been often notified in the Doctrine, as well of Heathen, as Chriſtian Vertues. And part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe no ſingle Vertue, in the want of the reſt can be enough to qualifie a Man for the State of the Heavenly Life, or render a Man ſo much as capable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Becauſe that Life doth require, as an Indiſpenſible Preparative for it, ſuch a Principle of Divine Life, or Holineſs, as comprehends the Habit and Diſpoſition at leaſt of all Goodneſs, and as is perfectly inconſiſtent with a total privation of any Real Vertue. So that if it were poſſible for a Man to have any ſuch Vertue in him, as Charity, with a total privation of Sobriety, Humility, Temperance and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety towards God, he could not be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of that Benefit, or Reward, which the Text ſpeaks of, that is, of having all his ſins covered, or perfectly diſcharged from all Puniſhment at the laſt Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Although that ſingle Vertue, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever imperfect, and inſincere, might poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly abate the degrees of Puniſhment, for
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:43236:39"/>the want of the reſt, as hath been inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed before.</p>
               <p>But although in the promiſes of this reward to any particular Vertue, or ſort of Good Works, there be a neceſſity of the foreſaid Synechdoche, yet in the Threatnings of Judgments to particular Vices, there is no neceſſity of any ſuch Figure. Becauſe, as there is no ſuch neceſſary Connexion of all ſorts of Vices, (as there is of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues) ſome of which are contrary and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with ſome others; ſo it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that any one Vice, notwithſtanding any freedom from others, is enough to reader a Man liable to the Sentence of Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: As in Humane Juſtice, one Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital Crime renders a man liable to death, notwithſtanding any poſſible Plea of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, as to other Crimes: And one Mortal Diſeaſe will kill a Man, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any freedom from other Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>So in the laſt judgement, if a Man be able to plead, (as many will be) that they were no Idolaters, Whoremaſters, Theeves, or other ſorts of Criminals: And that they are not guilty of ſtarving any body, or depriving them of their bread, robbing or oppreſſing, or caſting into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:43236:39"/>or other like breaches of Charity; no ſuch Plea will hold before the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judge, which will never change any thing upon a Man that he is not guilty of; nor doth he inſtance in any ſuch pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in this Monitory Deſcription of his laſt Judgement. He ſaith not, ye rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed me of my Meat, Drink, or Clothing, or ye wronged me by Violence or Fraud; but ye fed me not when I was hungry, ye clothed me not when I was naked, ye relieved me not in my Neceſſities nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did ye viſit, or comfort me in my Diſtreſſes: Go therefore ye curſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not for your Injuſtice or Injuries, but for your Uncharitableneſs. What could our bleſſed Lord mean by this negative man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of deſcribing his future Judgement but to warn all People of that vulgar Deceit, which they are ſo apt to fall into, that not being guilty of doing any body any wrong or harm (wherein alſo they judge very partially, upon groſs and falſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, without any regard to the many and great Injuries of the Heart and Tongue,) they muſt needs be excuſed at the Laſt Day. As if it were Charity enough to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver other ſins, not to have done any Wrong
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:43236:40"/>in matter of Fact to any Body, and not to take the Meat out of another mans mouth, were to Feed him, not to ſtrip him, or take away his Garment were to Clothe him I know no Plea of Common People ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently alledged as this, nor any ſo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull, or ſo contrary to the Expreſs mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our Saviours Deſcription of his own Judgment.</p>
               <p>I have inſiſted ſomething more largely upon this Teſtimony of our Saviour, as one that alone is ſufficient to confirm the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine here treated of. Nevertheleſs I ſhall proceed to the Allegation of a competent number of other Texts to the ſame purpoſe, which I judge to be partly neceſſary for the Conviction of a ſtrong Prejudice againſt this Doctrine in the minds of many Good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple amongſt us, and partly uſefull for the more effectual perſwaſion of all People to the ſtudy and practice of this Vertue, which the Apoſtle recommends to us with ſuch an Emphatical mark of Efficacy. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> before all things have fervent Charity: For Charity <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And becauſe the Texts already quoted have been taken out of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only, and chiefly from the Mouth of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:43236:40"/>our Saviour himſelf, I ſhall proceed to add ſome others of the ſame Authority, before I mention any out of the Old Teſtament. But before I produce any particular Text, I muſt demand the Conceſſion of this unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable Propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> That all Promiſes of entrance into Everlaſting Life or of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Heaven, made to the exerciſe of this Vertue, do neceſſarily ſuppoſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the Covering or Remiſſion of ſin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all ſin uncovered, <hi>i. e.</hi> unpardoned, is an invincible Barr to a mans entrance into that State, and renders him incapable of any place or reward in Heaven; becauſe a Man muſt firſt be juſtified from the Guilt of ſin, before he can be Glorified. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. <hi>Whom he hath juſtified, them he hath glorified.</hi> And it is no more poſſible for a Man to be Glorified without being Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, than it is to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven without being ſaved from Hell. Whatever therefore is, or can be available towards the Glorification of a ſinner, muſt needs be available towards his Salvation, or Deliverance from Condemnation, which imports ſuch Remiſſion or Non-imputation of ſin, as is ſpecially ſignified by the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of it. Therefore all Promiſes of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:43236:41"/>Entrance into Heaven, Heavenly Treaſure, Everlaſting Life or Rewaid, made by our Saviour himſelf, or by his Apoſtles in his Name to the habit or exerciſe of Charity, do neceſſarily imply the Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſin, to be hoped for upon the ſame account.</p>
               <p>For to ſay as ſome Divines do, that Charity and Good Works are neceſſary to Salvation, but not to Juſtification, ſeems to me no leſs than a real Contradiction. For ſo it muſt needs be, if it be ſpoken concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Final and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udicial Juſtification, which certainly is the moſt compleat and perfect Signification of that Word, Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ripture phraſe, being generally (though not always) oppoſed to Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation <hi>in ſenſu forenſi.</hi> As <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33, 34. <hi>It is God that juſtifieth, who ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn?</hi> and Prov. 17.15. <hi>He that juſtifieth the Wicked, and he that condemneth the Juſt, &amp;c.</hi> To be Juſtified is not to be Condemned, and what is it to be Saved, but not to be Condemed in the laſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? But if to be Saved, be not to be Condemned, and not to be Condemned is to be Juſtified; to ſay that Charity and Good Works are neceſſary to Salvation; or
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:43236:41"/>not Condemnation, and yet not neceſſary to Juſtification is a perfect Contradiction, equal to the Saying, that Charity is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and not neceſſary to Juſtification; but this by the way, only to anſwer a common Subterſuge from the Doctrine of the Text.</p>
               <p>Having thus premiſed this undeniable Poſtulate, I ſhall now proceed to alledge the particular promiſes of Salvation, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, and entrance into the Kingdom of Heaven, with the Poſſeſſion of Everlaſting rewards in that State, made to the habit and exerciſe of this Grace of Charity.</p>
               <p>In the Sermon upon the Mount, (beſides the Texts already cited from thence) I ſhall inſtance in two others, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.3, 4. <hi>But when thou doeſt thine Alms, let not thy Left hand know what thy Right hand doth, That thine Alms may be in Secret, and thy Father which ſeeth in ſecret, ſhall reward thee Openly.</hi> That this open Reward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to the Alms-giver, is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the Heavenly Reward, I preſume will not be queſtioned. And ver. 20. of the ſame Chapter, <hi>Lay up for your ſelves Treaſures in Heaven, where neither Moth nor Ruſt doth corrupt.</hi> Where, that our Saviour ſpeaks of the ſame practice of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:43236:42"/>Alms giving is evident by comparing the Text with its Parallel, <hi>Luke.</hi> 12.33. <hi>Sell all that you have, and give Alms, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your ſelves Baggs which wax not old, a Treaſure in the Heavens that faileth not, where no Thief approacheth, neither Moth corrupteth.</hi> Agreeable to the like words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21. <hi>Jeſus ſaid unto him, if thou wile be perfect go and ſell that thou haſt, and give to the Pope, and thou ſhalt have Treaſure in Heaven.</hi> To which Speech of our Saviour St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth undoubtedly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17, 18, 19. <hi>Charge them that are Rich in this world, that they do Good, that they be Rich in Good Works, ready to Diſtribute, willing to Communicate, laying up for themſelves a good Foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on Eternal Life.</hi> By which words the Apoſtle plainly ſignifies, ſuch Good Works as he ſpeaks of, to be a good Foundation of the Hope of Eternal Life, but ſo they could not be, unleſs they were alſo a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Hope of the Pardon of all ſins, becauſe the want of this Pardon deſtroys the Foundation of all Hope of Eternal Life.</p>
               <p>Another Text of the ſame importance is <hi>Luke</hi> 16.9. <hi>I ſay unto you, make to your
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:43236:42"/>ſelves Friends of the Mammon of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, that when ye fail, they may receive you into Everlaſting Habitations.</hi> Mammon is a Syriack word (the Language uſed by our Saviour) ſignifying Riches or worldly Wealth; and of the Reaſon, why they are called <hi>the Mammon of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs, or the unrighteous Mammon,</hi> ver. 11. a double Account may be given from the Context antecedent and conſequent. The antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Context is a Parable of the Unjuſt Steward, that provided for his future Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance (when he was warn'd out of his Office) by cheating his Maſter, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king himſelf Friends of his Maſters Debtors, by Defaulking what he pleaſed, from the juſt Accounts of their Debts, and putting them upon his own Intereſt, by ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Obligation. Now the Words of our Saviour in the Text cited, being the application of that Parable, may ſeem to imply the reaſon of that Phraſe, <hi>the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of unrighteouſneſs, or the unrighteous mammon,</hi> to be taken from the unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, which is frequently uſed in the gaining, holding and uſing of Worldly Riches. But another and better account of the ſame Term, may be collected from
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:43236:43"/>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> verſe; where the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ated and interpreted. <hi>If therefore ye have not been faithfull in the unrighteous Mammon; who will commit to your truſt the tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> riches.</hi> Where the unrighteous Mammon is oppoſed to the true Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or Riches. For the word <hi>Riches</hi> is not in the Greek, but underſtood in the Adjective, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the true,</hi> from whence it appears, that the reaſon of that te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <hi>unrighteouſneſs,</hi> is not to be drawn only from the manner of gaining, or u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Riches, but alſo from the proper na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and juſt Value thereof, which being compared with the only true Riches, is found to be falſe, vain and deceitfull. The only true Riches is that which is Spiritual and heavenly, conſiſting in true righteouſneſs, and the Reward thereof, in the Heavenly Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: therefore the Riches of this World are not the right, or true Riches, but are rather apt to deceive Men, and hinder them from obtaining the true Riches; whence our Saviour calls them the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of riches,</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> 4.19. <hi>the deceitfulneſs of riches</hi> choketh the ſeed of the word. And yet, ſo as they may be uſed, they may prove uſeful towards
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:43236:43"/>the gaining the true <hi>Riches,</hi> which is the thing ſignified by our Saviour in that Text; <hi>make to your ſelves friends of the mammon of unrighteouſneſs</hi> (the falſe, and deceitful Riches of the World) <hi>that when ye fail, i. e.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> When ye fail of holding them, or they fail you (as they muſt needs do, when ye come to die) <hi>they may receive you,</hi> i. e. you may be received: The word <hi>they,</hi> not relating neceſſarily to the word <hi>friends,</hi> but the Verb <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is rather to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood imperſonally, <hi>they may receive you,</hi> i. e. you may be received, as <hi>Luke</hi> 12.20. <hi>Thou fool, this night ſhall they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire thy ſoul,</hi> ſo it is in the Greek, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but well tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, <hi>thy ſoul ſhall be required of thee. Into everlaſting habitations,</hi> i. e. into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Now although in this Text no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs mention is made of the practice of Charity, yet that that is the thing meant (principally at leaſt) by the firſt words, <hi>make to your ſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs,</hi> no doubt can be made. And that being ſuppoſed to be the true Sence of thoſe words, the thing which I obſerve is this, that the practice of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:43236:44"/>is directed by our Saviour, to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the end, that a Man may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Heavenly Habitations, and therefore, that it muſt needs be ſome way available to that end (as I ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſhew more fully, in anſwer to the Objections made againſt this Doctrine) It being groſsly abſurd that any means ſhould be directed to be uſed for any end, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuppoſing that it can be ſome way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable thereunto. And becauſe the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Kingdom of Heaven, doth neceſſarily ſuppoſe the covering, or remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſin, which being uncovered, is an Invincible Barr to that entrance, I infer, that this Charity muſt be alſo available to the removing of this Ban, that is, to the covering of ſin.</p>
               <p>Another ſaying of our Saviours, which I take to be very agreeable to this, is in <hi>Luke</hi> 6.38. <hi>Give, and it ſhall be given unto you, good meaſure, preſſed down, and ſhaken together, and running over, ſhall men give into your boſom, for with the ſame meaſure that you mere withall, it ſhall be meaſured unto you again.</hi> The word <hi>Men</hi> is not in the Greek Text, but the Verb being the third Perſon plural,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:43236:44"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies no more then <hi>they ſhall give,</hi> and is to be interpreted by the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Vercle of the ſingular Number, uſed in the beginning of the verſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>it ſhall be given unto you.</hi> Which doth not ſignifie ſo much what ſhall be done by Men to the Charitable Perſon in this Life, as what ſhall be done by God for him, not in this Life only, or ſo much, as in that which is to come. For to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine the Senſe of the Text to the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Men, or of God, to the Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Perſon only in this Life, is to abate the Liberality of the Promiſe, ſo empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically expreſſed. Now although ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in this Life may be given by God to particular Good Works, without a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Pardon of ſin, yet ſo it cannot be in the Life to come, where a Man muſt firſt be diſcharged of his ſin, before he can be capable of any Reward of his Good Works. And even in this Life every tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Reward afforded to a ſinner, implies ſome Exemption from the extremity of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Puniſhment, becauſe it is inconſiſtent with it. Temporal Puniſhment, as well as Eternal is partly <hi>Privative,</hi> and partly <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive,</hi> conſiſting as well in the privation or
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:43236:45"/>want of temporal Good things, as in the ſuffering of ſenſible Evils. And temporal Reward muſt needs conſiſt in the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome temporal Privilege, or Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit which imports Coutradiction to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation thereof, which is part of the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſerved by him.</p>
               <p>I ſhall mention but one Text more from the Mouth of our Saviour, and that, is <hi>Luke</hi> 11.41. <hi>But rather give Alms of ſuch things as you have, and behold all things are clean unto you.</hi> The ſcope of which words moſt agreeable to the Context appears to be this, That whereas the Phariſees, by a ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Tradition did imagin, that it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for them to waſh their Hands before they did eat, to purge themſelves from any Pollution, that might render them Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, and ſo unfit to partake of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God in the uſe of their ordinary meat: our Saviour reprooving that Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Conceit, inſtructs them to a better way of purifying both Themſelves and their Meat: and that was <hi>by giving of Alms of what they poſſeſſed.</hi> That being a ſpecial teſtimony and fruit of Repentance, which is neceſſary and effectual to the Purgation of all Spiritual Pollution. A thing which
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:43236:45"/>by its Acceptance with God was fifted to procure his Parcon of all ſin, that might render them unworthy of partaking of any of his Benefits. The only thing that could pollute them and thoſe Creatures, which they were to receive, by Depriving them of the Bleſſing of God in the uſe of them was ſin. And to think that that could be cleanſed, or purged away by the outward Waſhing of their Hands, was a groſs piece of Superſtition: Although it wanted not ſome appearance of Foundation from the Ceremonial Precepts in <hi>Moſes's</hi> Law; for ſeveral Waſhings were enjoined to cleanſe the <hi>Jews</hi> from a ſort of Legal and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Pollution: but never were defigned for any Purgation from any Moral uncleanneſs or ſin. But the giving of Alms, according to the Ability of the Giver (ſignified by the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) doth indeed import ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a true and real Purification of the Heart, as it is an effect of Charity, which is the beſt Fruit of an unreigned Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, whereby the ſoul is cleanſed from the guilt and pollution of ſin.</p>
               <p>For there are two Parts of Repentance: the Firſt is <hi>to ceaſe to do Evil,</hi> and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>to learn to do Well.</hi> As 'tis deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:43236:46"/>by the Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi> Chap. 1. v. 16, 17, 18. A Text which I am to urge after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as a pregnant Confirmation of the Doctrine aſſerted in this Diſcourſe. <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt preaching the Baptiſm of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for the Remiſſion of ſins, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this upon his Auditory, that they ſhould <hi>bring forth Bruits worthy of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi> So did St. <hi>Paul</hi> in all places where he preached, <hi>Acts.</hi> 26.20. exhorting them <hi>to repent, and turn to God, and do Works meet for Repentance;</hi> ſuch indeed are all manner of Good Works and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining from Evil: And works of Mercy and Alms-giving being moſt eminent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Good Works, are by a common Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nechdoche of the Part for the Whole, put for all Good Works. And the whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of Repentance is ſometime deſcribed by them, as ſhall be ſhewn from ſeveral Texts of the Old Teſtament, which remain to be quoted in their due place.</p>
               <p>But as to the Senſe of that Speech of our Saviour, which I am yet ſpeaking of, it ſeemeth to agree with that of St. <hi>Paul, Tit.</hi> 1.15. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Pure all things are pure, but unto them that are defiled and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing, is nothing pure, but even their
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:43236:46"/>Mind and Conſcience is defiled.</hi> Where St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of all ſorts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Meats, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creatures of God (as our Saviour doth in this Speech) declaring the Uſe of them <hi>to the Pure, i. e.</hi> to all penitent Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers (oppoſed to them that are defiled and unbelieving, <hi>whoſe Mind and Conſcience is defiled</hi> with ſin unrepented of) are pure. The only Difference of theſe two Sayings ſeemeth to be this: That whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of a general Purity, our Saviour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the ſame thing Synechdochically, by a particular eminent Inſtance of Good Works, ſuppoſed to proceed from a common principle of Sanctification &amp; Purity of Heart.</p>
               <p>To conclude my Animadverſion upon the Text, that which our Saviour means is, as if he had ſaid, to go about to cleanſe the Body, without regard to the Soul, is vain and unprofitable. But on the contrary, the Soul being cleanſed by Repentance, teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſuch an eminent Fruit of it, as is the giving of Alms (ſuppoſed to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in their Meaſure, and proportionable to the Ability of the Giver) all things (not forbidden by God) are clean, and free to be uſed without fear of Pollution, and with confidence of his Bleſſing.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:43236:47"/>
               <p>If this be not the Meaning of our Saviour in this obſcure Text. I know not what it ſhould be. But if it be ſo, it plainly and fully confirms the Doctrine which I have in hand, <hi>viz.</hi> that Charity is a ſpecial and effectual means for the Covering of ſin, which is all one with the Cleanſing from the Guilt of it.</p>
               <p>But ſome Proteſtant Expoſitor preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced againſt this Doctrine, have utterly changed the Senſe of our Saviour in this Speech, which they will not allow to be deſigned by him for any Direction or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the means of Cleanſing men from the Guilt of ſin: But to be ſpoken Ironically in reference to a common Opinion and Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the <hi>Jews,
<note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Lightfoots</hi> Horae. Hebr.</note> viz.</hi> that Alms is equipollent to all the precepts of the Law, and enough to purge away ſin, and ſave from Hell; and this Sentence to be cited from them by way of Irriſion and Reprehenſion, rather then with Approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo not to be uttered as his own words or meaning; but this Interpretation ſeems to be forced, as having no other Foundation, then the Prejudice of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors againſt the Doctrine which we are
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:43236:47"/>treating of, confirmed by this, and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Saying of our Saviour.</p>
               <p>I ſhall add but one Text more out of the New Teſtament; <hi>viz.</hi> that of St. <hi>Paul, Hebr.</hi> 13.16. <hi>To do good, and to diſtribute forget not, for with ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed:</hi> Where I ſhall not inſiſt upon the Latine Tranſlations, which may ſeem more expreſſly to favour our Doctrine, by the words <hi>promeretur,</hi> vulg. <hi>placatur,</hi> vel <hi>conciliatur,</hi> ſignifying God to be <hi>appeaſed, reconciled</hi> and <hi>made friends</hi> by works of Charity: But content my ſelf with our Engliſh Tranſlation, moſt literally agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Greek Word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>God is well pleaſed.</hi> Which word doth as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though not ſo expreſsly confirm our Doctrine, as any of the Latine Words fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, uſed by Learned Interpreters, do. For whatſoever Good Works God is truly pleaſed with, muſt needs be profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the averting his Diſpleaſure, from the Perſon that doth them, if he be any ways liable thereto, and whatſoever tends to the Averting his Diſpleaſure, tends equally to the Averting the Puniſhment of ſin, which is the Senſe that I aſſert of St. <hi>Peters</hi> phraſe of Covering of ſins. Nor can God be well
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:43236:48"/>pleaſed with any Action of a ſinner, till he be in ſome meaſure at leaſt reconciled to him, and diſpoſed to the Pardon of his ſin. Other Texts out of the New Teſtament will be alledged afterward in Anſwer to the Objections againſt the Doctrine</p>
               <p>At preſent I ſhall only add a few more of equal Authority out of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, beginning with that of Solomon <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.21. <hi>He that deſpiſeth his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſinneth, but he that hath mercy on the poor, happy is he.</hi> The Engliſh An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notation upon this Text, commonly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the Aſſembly of Divines, is remarkable in theſe words. <q rend="margQuotes">He that will not give to the poor, ſhall be puniſhed as a ſinner, although he takes nothing from them, or becauſe it is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety and Priviledge of Charity to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a multitude of ſins, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.20. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8. He that deſpiſeth his neighbour ſinneth, may be alſo, and is by ſome interpreted, ſhall be found a ſinner, all his ſins ſhall be reckoned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and he ſhall be puniſhed without any mitigation. So 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 1.21. I and my ſon ſhall be ſinners, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſhall be proceeded againſt as offenders, ſin will
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:43236:48"/>be imputed unto us.</q> Where we find the ſame Interpretation of the Text, in St. <hi>Peter,</hi> which is given by us, allowed by theſe Annotators, who are far enough from all ſuſpicion of favour to any Popiſh Doctrines. Notwithſtanding the ſame In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters do give the other Sence of St. <hi>Peters</hi> words only in their Notes upon that place, making them to relate to the ſins of others, thereby making peace. But this Interpretation is grounded only upon the parallel Text of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> cited by them, and as they think, by the Apoſtle, which Objection hath been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered before. Now the forementioned Sence of the firſt Branch of the Text, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.21. given by the Annotator, doth determine the ſecond, by way of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the firſt, to ſignifie that Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs which is promiſed to him that hath mercy on the poor, to conſiſt in the non-imputation, covering, or remiſſion of his ſins.</p>
               <p>But a more indubitable Teſtimony out of the ſame Book, to confirm this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is in Chap. 16.6. <hi>by mercy and truth iniquity is purged.</hi> The vulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin reads <hi>redimitur, is redeemed,</hi> Junius and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:43236:49"/>Tremellius, <hi>expiatur, is expiate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the proper ſignification of the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>placavit, expiavit,</hi> ſo the meaning of the words is, that by the practice of theſe Vertues, the Pardon of ſin is impetrated, or obtained. And one would think this Expoſition of the wiſe mans words, ſhould be paſt all doubt. But becauſe the admiſſion of it imports an irrefragable confirmation of the Doctrine, which we labour to defend, ſome Interpreters out of meer prejudice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Doctrine, have found out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meaning of the words, affording no manner of favour to this concluſion. Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Mercy and Truth, ſpoken of in this Text, are to be referred to God only, and not at all to Men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> making the Sence to be, that iniquity is purged by the Mercy and Truth of God, without any reſpect to thoſe Vertues, as practiſed by Men.</p>
               <p>But whether this Interpretation be not forced to comply with the opinion of them that advance it; or to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other, which is ſo obvious and plain, muſt be left to the judgement of the Impartial and Ingenuous Reader, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:43236:49"/>I am not willing to trouble him with a tedious confutation of it.</p>
               <p>Another Text to this purpoſe is that of <hi>Daniel</hi> 4.27. <hi>Wherefore O King, let my counſel be acceptable unto thee, and break off thy ſins by righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> (or by Alms,
<note place="margin">Vulg. Latin, Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint, Munſter. Syriack, Arabick, de Dieu. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> as the word is there rendred by many learned Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and as the ſame word is often uſed in the Old Teſtament) <hi>and thine iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by ſhewing mercy to the Poor: if it may be a lengthening to thy tranquillity, or a healing of thine error,</hi> as it is in the Margent: where to let paſs the conteſt about the Tranſlation of the Verb, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whether it ought to be as we have it, according to other Proteſtant Tranſlations, <hi>break off,</hi> or as it is in the Septuagint, vulgar Latin, Syriack, Arabick, and very many other Tranſlators, <hi>redeem thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> it is evident that the Prophets counſel to the King was given to the end, that he might obtain ſome remiſſion of his ſin, and avoid the extremity of the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning declared in the foregoing verſes. And the matter of that counſel conſiſting in the practice of Charity, it is likewiſe evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:43236:50"/>that in the judgement of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſuch Charity is a thing available to that end, otherwiſe his counſel was vain, and unprofitable.</p>
               <p>The like counſel is given by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Chap. 1.16, 17, 18. verſes, to the people of <hi>Judah,</hi> after a ſevere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance of Gods diſpleaſure, threatning their Deſtruction, and rejecting their hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical ſervices. He tells them what they ſhould do, to eſcape that Puniſhment of their ſin, and gain a full remiſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Waſh you, make you clean, put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes, ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well. ſeek judgement, relieve the oppreſſed, judge the fatherleſs, plead for the widow; come now, and let us reaſon together, ſaith the Lord, though your ſins be as ſcarlet, they ſhall be as white as ſnow, though they be red like crimſon, they ſhall be us wooll.</hi> If theſe words uttered by the Prophet in the name of the Lord, do not confirm that Senſe of the Apoſtle which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt for, I know not what words will do it. He that is not abundantly ſatisfied with the Evidence of theſe Texts of the New and Old Teſtament, may ſee more
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:43236:50"/>to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41.1. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. from the 7<hi rend="sup">t•</hi> verſe to the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.7. <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.8, 9. And when he hath conſidered theſe Canonical Texts, he may caſt his eye upon two or three A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryphals, <hi>Tob.</hi> 4.7, 8, 9, 10, 11. and Chap. 12.9. <hi>For Alms doth deliver from death, and ſhall purge away all ſin.</hi> Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticus 3.30. <hi>Water will quench a fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, and Alms maketh an Atonement for ſin.</hi> The authority of theſe Texts, doth not ſo much teſt upon the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Authors, as upon <hi>the general Senſe of the Jewiſh Church,</hi> which they are juſtly preſumed to deliver eſpecially while their Doctrine is found ſo agreeable to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Scriptures, which were the Rule of their Faith. To tranſcribe all the Texts, which are to be found in the Bible to this purpoſe, and make ſuch particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks upon them, as we have done upon thoſe few, which we have cited before, would ſwell the Diſcourſe, and be a Work of Supererogation, by which we cannot hope to merit ſo much of the Reader, as perhaps we may do by ſparing his pains, and our own.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:43236:51"/>
               <head>CHAP IV.</head>
               <p>HAving now ſufficiently (as we think) confirmed the General Doctrine, founded upon this Text of St. <hi>Peter:</hi> we are to proceed according to our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to the anſwering ſome Objections, which have been or may be made againſt this Sence of the words. And I ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with that which ſeems to be moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable,</p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>Objection.</hi> Namely, that theſe words of the Apoſtle are quoted, or borrowed from a Proverb of Solomons, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Hatred ſtirreth up ſtrife, but love covereth all ſins.</hi> Where by the Antithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis of the two parts of the Sentence, it is paſt all doubt, that the ſins to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by love, muſt be the ſins of others, and not of the Charitable Perſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To this may be anſwered. 1. That it is no way evident, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle did intend any quotation of that Proverb, there being no ſuch intimation thereof in this Text, as is uſual in other quotations out of the Old Teſtament, by thoſe words, <hi>as it is written,</hi> or the like,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:43236:51"/>uſed by this ſame Apoſtle in this Epiſtle, Chap. 1.16. <hi>Becauſe it is written, be ye Holy, as I am Holy.</hi> And as it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that he doth not quote the whole Proverb, whiles he leaves out the firſt part, <hi>Hatred ſtirreth up ſtrife;</hi> ſo, that he doth not cite the ſecond part verba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim, is plain, by comparing the Texts. Whereof one ſaith, <hi>love covereth all ſins,</hi> the other only <hi>a multitude of ſins.</hi> But in the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> which is generally fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in quotations out of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, in the New, a far greater diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is found, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. So it is in the <hi>Septuagint;</hi> not agreeing ſo much as in one word with St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed quotation, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The Hebrew Text indeed is ſomething more agreeable to St. <hi>Peters</hi> words.</p>
               <p>But then 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Suppoſe that the Apoſtle did allude unto the words of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb (as is not improbable) it doth not therefore follow that he intended the ſame Sence, it being very uſual with our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelf, and the Evangeliſts and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, by way of accommodation, to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:43236:52"/>make uſe of Texts and Sayings in the Old Teſtament, in a different Sence from that which did belong to them there. As in <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.15. and 23. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.15. and elſewhere frequently. And this Anſwer I take to be ſufficient for this firſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection againſt our Interpretation of St. <hi>Peters</hi> words.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Objection.</hi> But another main Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and that which is moſt like to be inſiſted upon againſt this Interpretation, is, that it ſeems to favour the Popiſh Doctrines of Merit, Satisfaction and Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by Works, and to be repugnant to the Evangelical Doctrine of the moſt full, perfect, and ſufficient Expiation, and Satisfaction for the ſins of the whole World, made only by the Sacrifice of Chriſts death, and applied only by Faith. The covering and pardon of ſin, is the Effect of Gods grace granted only upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of Chriſts death, upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a true Faith in him wrought by the Spirit of God through the hearing of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To this Objection I anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That although ſome Papiſts interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Text as I do, may be found to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:43236:52"/>alledge it among other Texts, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of ſome of the Doctrines men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Objection; yet neither is this Senſe vouched by all Interpreters of their Profeſſion; nor can any of thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines be further evinced, or confirmed from this Text, ſo underſtood, then it may be from other Texts before alledged for the Confirmation of the Doctrine, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which the Objection is made. Nor is the free grace of God, or the ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of that Expiation, or Satisfaction which was made by the death of Chriſt, any more abated by this Doctrine, than it is by that which all the forementioned Texts import.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The words <hi>Merit</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> are known to have been familiarly uſed, in reference to Good Works, by the moſt ancient of the <hi>Latin Fathers,</hi> and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly by St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> (one of the moſt Primitive) in a Catholick Orthodox Senſe. Both the words are Innocent in the Senſe of the Fathers, though they have been perverted by the Schoolmen.</p>
               <p>And Juſtification by Works is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as true in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Sence, as 'tis falſe in St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> The late Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:43236:53"/>that have been concerning theſe Points, do not ſo much reſpect the words, as the extravagant Senſe, that hath been put upon them by the Schoolmen, who have intangled and corrupted a great part of Chriſtian Doctrine, by their misinterpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fathers: determining the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of their Popular Expreſſions, by their own Capricious and Litigious Conceits, into ſuch Dogmatical Senſe, as was never thought of by the Antients. But in the particular Controverſies about Merit, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and Juſtification by Works, there hath been ſo much of Logomachy, or word-bate, as might (in my opinion) be fairly compromiſed, or accorded by Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Arbitratours, whoſe minds were free from all prejudice, but that againſt Contention and Diviſion: and were more zealous for Unity and Concord, than for diſputable and opinionative Truth. But for to undertake that task in this place would not be reaſonable.</p>
               <p>That all Pardon of ſin is founded upon the Expiation, or Propitiation made by the Bloud of Chriſt, and granted, or obtained only by the Free Grace of God, is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by any Sect or Party of Chriſtians,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:43236:53"/>that I know of. Although ſome Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences have been about the Conditions of this Grant. For to ſay, that this Grace is granted without any Condition or Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Receiver, is, in my Judgment, to deny a great part of the Scriptures, as well of the New Teſtament, as of the Old, deſtructive as well of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, as of the Old: no more Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian than Anti-evangelical.</p>
               <p>Doubtleſs it is of Free Grace that God will pardon a ſinner, upon any Condition, Nor is it poſſible for us to do any thing, ſufficient to make Satisfaction for our ſins, or to merit the Forgiveneſs of them, in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor of Juſtice, becauſe all that is in our Power to do, is no more then our Duty, if God requires it. And all that we do, is much leſs. And as the duty of Well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the utmoſt Extent, is a juſt Debt of Thankfulneſs at leaſt, if not of Preceptive Obligation to Almighty God, to whom we owe our ſelves, and all that we have or can do. So the Puniſhment we are liable to for neglecting our Duty, or acting contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereunto in our Evil doings, is another Debt, by our Saviours account ſignified to us in that Form of Prayer which he hath
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:43236:54"/>taught us to uſe: <hi>Forgive us our Debts, as we forgive our Debtors, Mat.</hi> 6.12. But it is altogether unreaſonable one Debt can be diſcharged by the Payment of another, eſpecially when the Payment falls ſo much ſhort of the old Debt, as it doth in any thing we do. Beſides that upon a due ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Charity it ſelf, and every Good Work that can be done by us; doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our debt to God, becauſe it cannot be done without his Grace.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs God of his Free Grace hath promiſed the Remiſſion of ſin, upon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Conditions declared in his Word, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which, this of Charity is one, that by a common Synechdoche of a Part for the Whole, includes all the reſt. And whereas in the New Teſtament Faith in Chriſt is more commonly propounded, as the Condition of Juſtification, importing the Remiſſion of ſin, it is to be conſidered, that this Faith is ſo far from excluding Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that it is expreſſly ſaid to include it, by St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, the ſuppoſed Author of the Doctrine of Juſtification by Faith without Works, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. <hi>For in Chriſt Jeſus neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, but Faith which
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:43236:54"/>worketh by Love.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whether the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, be to be underſtood in a Paſſive ſenſe, (as moſt commonly it is elſewhere in Scripture, and in other Books: and as it is here ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by the <hi>Syriack</hi> Tranſlator, and ſo meaning that Faith is <hi>actuated, perfected, and made effectual</hi> by Love) or in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive ſenſe, as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation gives it, ſignifying the <hi>Efficacy, Energy</hi> or <hi>Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of Faith only. The Meaning of the Apoſtle by the Addition of theſe Words, can be no other then to limit, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the nature of that Faith, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable to Juſtification, from an hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, dead, and ineffectual Faith, which is altogether invalid, availing nothing at all to the Effect of Juſtification. The Active ſenſe of the Word, as well as the Paſſive, ſerving to declare the true Nature and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Juſtifying Faith to be <hi>Energeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Practical, i. e.</hi> producing ſuch ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the Will, as are agreeable to the entire Object of it: that is, to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Chriſt, his Doctrine and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, as well as ſuch as reſpect only the Effect of Redemption, or Expiation of ſin by his Death. And ſuch is the neceſſity of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:43236:55"/>this Charity, by the Doctrine of the ſame Apoſtle, that he elſewhere ſaith, <hi>Though I have all Faith, ſo that I could remove Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and have not Charity, it profiteth me nothing,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. Where by <hi>all Faith,</hi> undoubtedly is meant, all the Faith that can be had without Charity, and needs not to be reſtrained to the particular <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>extraordinary Gift of the Faith of Miracles,</hi> whereof he ſpeaks in the former Chapter ver. 12.</p>
               <p>To this Purpoſe St. <hi>James</hi> Chap. 2.22. ſaith, <hi>Faith is made perfect by Works;</hi> not excluding any ſort of Good Works, but ſpecially treating of the works of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as appears by the Context, from verſe the 13. to the 18. And whereas he ſaith, <hi>Faith is made perfect by Works,</hi> he ſpeaks not only of a Gradual Perfection, or of the Conſummation or Preſervation of Faith, or of the Ornament, Demonſtration, or ſignal evidence of Faith, as ſome would have it; but of ſuch an eſſential and formal Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as is neceſſary to the nature of Truth, and ſincerity of Faith, as appears by that repeated Sentence, both before and after theſe Words, ver. 17. <hi>Faith without Works is dead,</hi> and ver. 26. <hi>As the Body without
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:43236:55"/>the Spirit is dead; ſo Faith without Works is dead alſo.</hi> Whether by <hi>the Spirit</hi> he means <hi>the Breath</hi> (as ſome take it, becauſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Spiritus,</hi> ſometime ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies no more) or rather <hi>the Soul,</hi> which is the moſt uſual Senſe of the word in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Meaning comes all to one, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, that an idle or fruitleſs Faith hath no more of Spiritual Life or Reality in it, than a Body can have without Breath, or without a Soul: and therefore is no more a true and unfeigned Faith, than a dead Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſs is a human Body.</p>
               <p>Indeed the true juſtifying, ſaving Faith in the practical Notion, which is the only true Notion of it, includes Charity, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all other Good Works, as I have elſewhere largely ſhewed: So that if Faith be neceſſary to the Covering or Remiſſion of ſin, Charity is ſo too. But the common Anſwer to theſe, and all other Texts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to evince the Neceſſity of Charity and Good Works, to the Salvation of a ſinner, is, that they prove only <hi>a neceſſity of Preſence and Concomitancy,</hi> or at moſt <hi>a neceſſity of Conſequence,</hi> not <hi>of Efficacy,</hi> that is, that this Neceſſity doth not reſpect <hi>the End or Effect</hi> of Faith, in the Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:43236:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>or Salvation of the Believeer, but proceeds only from the common nature and principle of that Faith, which is an effect of the Spirit of God: the neceſſary Fruits whereof do conſiſt in Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which diſtinct Vertues, with their proper Works, do not contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute any thing to the Effect of our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but are meer Concomitants, or at moſt but gratefull Effects of that Faith which juſtifieth us. Which uſeth to be illuſtrated by a Similitude borrowed from the natural and animal Life, wherein the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar faculties of Seeing, or taking hold of a thing by the Touch, do neceſſarily imply ſuch a common Principle of ſenſitive Life, as doth alſo comprehend the powers and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of Hearing, Smelling and Taſting, yet none of theſe Faculties, or any act of them do, or can contribute any thing effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently to the effect of Seeing, Apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or laying hold of an Object: So the Grace of Charity, or Love to God, and Man, together with all thoſe other Fruits of the Spirit, which are mentioned by the Apoſtle, and all the Effects and Works, which do proceed from them, are indeed neceſſary Concomitants of ſuch a Faith, as
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:43236:56"/>juſtifies or ſaves a Man, but do contribute no more, nor have any more Efficacy to this effect of Juſtification and Salvation, than the diſtinct Faculties of other Senſes, do to the effect of Seeing. This I take to be a true Account of their Senſe, that aſſert the Doctrine of Juſtification, and Pardon of ſin by Faith only, as that imports a habit, or act really diſtinct, though not ſeparated from other Chriſtian Vertues.</p>
               <p>In oppoſition to this Opinion contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Doctrine which I maintain to be the Senſe of the Apoſtle in this Text, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, as hath been ſeen, by many others, I am engaged to prove that Charity, and Good Works are neceſſary to the Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſinner, that is, to the Remiſſion of his ſin, not only by way of Concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy, or joint Preſence with Faith, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent to it, but alſo by way of moral Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy as a Condition or Means to obtain that Effect.</p>
               <p>This I hope will be ſufficiently done by the following Arguments, this one po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate or concluſion (which I ſuppoſe will not be denied) being firſt granted me, <hi>viz.</hi> That if any thing elſe beſide the habit or act of Faith, conſidered as really diſtinct
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:43236:57"/>from other Chriſtian Vertues or Acts, be effectual or available to the Remiſſion of ſin, then Charity is, or may be ſo, in as much as that is one of the moſt Excellent of Chriſtian Vertues, moſt agreeable to the Nature of God, and conſequently moſt pleaſing to him. So that if that be not available to this End, nothing elſe beſides Faith, can be ſo. This Propoſition being granted, I argue as followeth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Argument.</hi> If it be certain from Scripture, and we be bound to believe, that nothing which can be done by us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſuch a Faith, as is ſuppoſed to be really diſtinct (though not ſeparate) from all Good Works, can be of any Efficacy towards the remiſſion of our ſins, then ought nothing elſe to be done by us to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that end, becauſe every ſuch other act done to this end, would by this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition be perfectly vain and unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and not ſo only, but alſo contrary to our obliged belief. And then to pray for the forgiveneſs of our ſins, that being an act diſtinct from Faith, would be not only needleſs and uſeleſs, but unlawful; eſpecially if it ſhould be acted with any opinion, hope, or belief, that ſuch a prayer
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:43236:57"/>could avail us any thing in order to this end, or that this end could any way be promoted by our Prayers. But this is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to our Saviours Precept in that Form of Prayer, which he hath taught us to uſe, wherein we are directed to pray, that God will <hi>forgive us our treſpaſſes, as we forgive them that treſpaſs againſt us.</hi> And contrary to the advice of St. <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Acts 8.22. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent therefore of this thy wickedneſs, and pray God, if perhaps the thought of thine heart may be forgiven thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where alſo it is to be noted, that the Apoſtle adviſeth him not only to pray for the forgiveneſs of his ſin, but alſo to repent of it in order to the ſame end. The ſame advice is given by the ſame Apoſtle to the Jews in the firſt Sermon which he made unto them, after the reception of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37, 38. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving convinced them of their hainous ſin in the murder of the Lord Jeſus, and made them ſenſible of it: <hi>Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their hearts, and ſaid unto</hi> Peter <hi>and the reſt of the Apoſtles, men and brethren, what ſhall we do. Then</hi> Peter <hi>ſaid unto them, repent and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:43236:58"/>be baptizid every one of you, in the name of Jeſus Chriſt, for the remiſſion of ſins.</hi> Where 'tis obſervable, that whiles two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things are preſcribed by the Apoſtle to be done, in order to the remiſſion of ſin, <hi>viz. to repent,</hi> and <hi>to be baptized,</hi> no mention is made of Faith, other then is included in thoſe words, <hi>be baptized in the name of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which do indeed neceſſarily imply the act of Faith. But beſides this Baptiſm, which is one thing required to be done for the remiſſion of ſins, Repentance alſo, which is another thing, is expreſsly required, as neceſſary to this end: not in that Text only, but in an hundred others of both Teſtaments, from whence it is that this remiſſion of ſin is mentioned as the ſignal effect of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.4. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.3. <hi>John</hi> is ſaid to have preached the <hi>Baptiſm of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for the Remiſſion of ſin.</hi> And in the Conjunction of theſe two things, the Sum of the Goſpel to be preached to all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is compriſed by our Saviour in St. <hi>Luke,</hi> chap. 24.47. <hi>That Repentance and Remiſſion of ſin ſhould be preached in his Name to all Nations.</hi> Hence alſo is the ſame called <hi>Repentance unto Life, Acts.</hi> 11.18.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:43236:58"/>and <hi>Repentance to Salvation,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9.</p>
               <p>From which Texts it doth ſufficiently appear, not only that Repentance is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary unto the Remiſſion of ſin, and to Life and Salvation, as a Condition, or <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa ſine quâ non,</hi> but that it is alſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and really available to theſe Ends: For to call that <hi>Repentance unto Life,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to Salvation,</hi> which contributes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, nor hath any manner of Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy to theſe Ends, is an abſurd Form of words. And if the Prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>unto,</hi> doth not ſignifie ſome kind of Efficacy, or Qualification for theſe Ends, it ſignifies juſt nothing. But if it doth ſignifie any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Efficacy to this End, one of theſe Things muſt needs be true: either that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is the ſame thing with that Faith, which abſtracts from Works, as an Act re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally diſtinct from them all, which is a plain Contradiction: or that ſomething beſides Faith, and really diſtinct from it, is effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and available to the Remiſſion of ſins, which is the thing that was to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated.</p>
               <p>Thus I have named <hi>two Things beſides Faith,</hi> which are generally neceſſary to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:43236:59"/>of ſin, <hi>viz. Prayer</hi> and <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> Whereunto might be added the practice of Faſting, Mourning, Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Confeſſion of ſin, as things fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently mentioned in Scripture, with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription to their uſe, in order to this end. I forbear to cite the particular Texts, wherein theſe things are preſcribed; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are all but <hi>appendages, or parts of the general duty of Repentance.</hi> Nor are theſe things neceſſary to this effect barely, and only by their antecedent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, as meet and convenient preparatives for this Grace of Pardon, but alſo by, and in reſpect of ſuch a Moral Efficacy, and Prevalency, as they are juſtly preſumed to have, by their declared acceptance with God, which is all the Efficacy that can be reaſonably attributed to Faith it ſelf. And if upon the ſtreſs of this Argument, it ſhould be ſaid that Faith in the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Senſe, as a living energetical opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive habit, doth include Repentance, with all the proper fruits thereof, the whole Queſtion is yielded. For then to ſay, that Faith is available for the remiſſion, or covering of ſin, is to ſay, that Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Prayer, Charity, and Good Works
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:43236:59"/>are ſo too, which is all we contend for. It being far from our meaning to exclude Faith from any neceſſary concurrence to this effect of Charity, that is to ſay, that Charity without Faith can cover ſin. For neither can Chriſtian Charity be without Faith, nor if it could, would it be any wiſe effectual to this end. The only thing that we aſſert is, that Charity together with Faith, and as a proper, and moſt Excellent Fruit of it, is available to this end. And the ſumm of the Argument, which we have here urged to confirm this Aſſertion is this,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That if nothing but Faith can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable to this end, then ought nothing to be done in order to it, but believing. And Prayer, Repentance, Humiliation, and Confeſſion of ſin (notwithſtanding that in Scripture they be all preſcribed, as means to be uſed to this end) are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſeleſs, or needleſs, but unlawfull to be practiſed with reſpect to this end. Or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that if any of theſe things be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable to this purpoſe, ſo alſo is Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. This is our firſt Argument.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Argument.</hi> If Charity and Good Works of any ſort be not available to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:43236:60"/>the obtainment of remiſſion of ſin, Eternal Life, and Salvation; then do all promiſes of theſe Benefits made to the uſe and exerciſe of theſe means, ſignifie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or at leaſt they muſt needs loſe all power and ſignification of Motives to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe Duties. For how can that be conſidered as a reaſonable Motive to any act, which doth no way promote it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the General Deſign and end of all <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Promiſes,</hi> is to encourage, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, and move the Perſons to whom they are made, to the performance of thoſe Conditions and Acts which are recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the reſpective Promiſes, upon the hope of obtaining the promiſed Benefits, by thoſe means. But this hope can have no foundation, without the believing, that the performance of thoſe Conditions will be ſome ways effectual to the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe Benefits. But if the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of ſuch Acts and Conditions muſt be believed to contribute nothing at all to the obtainment of theſe Benefits, the forementioned Faith in the Promiſes, which is the only foundation of the hope, is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroyed. And by conſequence the ſaid Promiſes are deprived of all Vertue,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:43236:60"/>or power of Motives, to the practices whereunto they are annexed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Argument.</hi> All Precepts, Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Counſels (ſuch as that in our Text) to the practice of Charity, or any other Chriſtian Vertue, beſide Faith, ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by ſuch Motives as are no ways pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted by the Acts whereunto we are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted, are vain, and deluſory. Were ſuch Precepts and Exhortations delivered ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and abſolutely, as only declarative of our Duty, or deſigned only to move Men to their Duties, as Teſtimonies of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude or Thankfulneſs for thoſe Benefits, which we receive only by Faith (as ſome late Divines would have them) they would indeed be reaſonable upon that account. But when they are expreſsly urged, as in this Text, and many others they are, to move Men to the Practice of particular Duties, as means to obtain the propoſed Benefits, what can they ſignifie, but a plain impoſing upon us, or abuſing our minds, and perverting our Faith, ſuppoſing that the doing of thoſe things, whereto we are exhorted, can nothing avail us to thoſe ends? What can ſuch Exhortations ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie more then if a man ſhould be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:43236:61"/>to ſtretch forth his hands to behold the Glory of the Heavens, or to open his eyes to hear the ſweet Melody of Muſick.</p>
               <p>But the force of theſe Arguments is by many late Divines thought to be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently avoided, by alledging, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be true, that Faith is the only thing, that is effectual to Juſtification, or remiſſion of ſin, and that no other Act or Vertue can contribute any thing to this end, yet neither are the forementioned Promiſes, nor the Exhortations void, or uſeleſs in reference to this effect.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe there is a Neceſſity of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, though not of efficacy, of thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Acts and Vertues, which are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Promiſes and Exhortations. And ſo Charity amongſt other things may be a <hi>cauſa ſine quâ non,</hi> of Salvation and remiſſion of ſin, in reſpect of its neceſſary preſence together with Faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the ſame things are neceſſary to the verification of Faith, <hi>i. e.</hi> to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the Truth of it, though they have no concurrent efficacy with Faith, to the Juſtification or Salvation of the Believer.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe the practice of theſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:43236:61"/>is neceſſary, or at leaſt uſefull for the aſſurance of a mans Juſtification, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin, and Salvation, though it be no ways effectual to any of thoſe ends, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in themſelves. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10. <hi>For God is not unrighteous to forget your work, and labour of love, which ye have ſhewed towards his name, in that ye have mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to the Saints, and do miniſter.</hi> And 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 10, 11. <hi>And beſides all this giving all diligence, add to your faith ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and to vertue knowledge, and to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge temperance, and to temperance patience, and to patience godlineſs, and to godlineſs brotherly kindneſs, and to brotherly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, charity,</hi> i. e. an univerſal Charity, extended to all men, as well as Chriſtian Brethren. <hi>Wherefore ye rather give di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to make your calling and election ſure</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as it is in ſome Greek Copies, and though theſe words are left out in our own, and other Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations, becauſe they are ſo in ordinary Greek Copies, yet the Senſe of them is confeſſedly included in all readings) <hi>for ſo an entrance ſhall be given you abundantly, into the everlaſting kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And 1 <hi>Joh.</hi>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:43236:62"/>3.18, 19. <hi>My little children, let us not love in word, nor in tongue, but in deed and in truth. And hereby we know, that we are of the truth, and ſhall aſſure our hearts before him;</hi> So 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.14. <hi>We know that we have paſſed from death unto Life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we love the brethren.</hi> By theſe Texts, and many more of like Senſe, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that Charity is uſefull to procure a mans aſſurance of thoſe Benefits, which are ſuppoſed to be obtained by Faith only.</p>
               <p>Another verbal evaſion of all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments which are produced for the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual concurrence of Charity and Good Works to the attainment of the great Benefits of final Juſtification and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath been vulgarly expreſſed by that trite ſaying of the Latin Father, <hi>Bernard. Bona opera ſunt via ad regnum, non cauſa regnandi, Good Works are indeed the way to the kingdom of Heaven, but not the cauſe of reigning.</hi> Which words applied to the Doctrine by us grounded upon the words of the Apoſtle, muſt have this Senſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That Charity is the way to obtain the covering, or non-imputation of ſin, but no cauſe of it, <hi>i. e,</hi> a means, but not a cauſe; a very nice diſtinction, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered further hereafter.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:43236:62"/>
               <p>This I take to be a juſt account of the chief Anſwers, that have been made to the premiſed Arguments, from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and exhortations of Scripture, for the efficacy or validity of Charity and Good Works, unto the remiſſion of ſin, and the Salvation of a ſinner.</p>
               <p>Now in order to a ſufficient reply to theſe Anſwers, I think it neceſſary in this place to ſay ſomething by way of expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Queſtion (tending to the clearing of the true Senſe, and meaning of the Doctrine) what is meant by that Efficacy, which any act, that can be done by men, may have towards the remiſſion of their ſins, their Juſtification and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p>It is evident, that all theſe things are the proper and peculiar Acts and Effects of God himſelf, who is the agent of effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe of them all. And therefore 'tis impoſſible that any Humane Act ſhould have any direct or immediate influence, or efficiency upon theſe Effects. <hi>Who can forgive ſins, but God?</hi> And 'tis God that juſtifies, and ſaves actively. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Efficacy that can be in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Acts towards theſe effects, can be no
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:43236:63"/>more than <hi>preparative</hi> or <hi>paſſive.</hi> And what can that ſignifie more, than that they are certain Diſpoſitions and Qualifications of the Patient, or Subject to receive theſe Effects of Divine Grace. Nor can Faith it ſelf have any other influence or efficacy upon theſe Effects, any more than Charity. Faith it ſelf doth neither pardon our ſin, or contribute any thing to that Divine Act, by which we are pardoned. Neither doth qualifie or ſave us, any otherwiſe then by making ſuch a Change or Qualification in us, whereupon this Grace of Juſtification to Life, is freely given us of God.</p>
               <p>But againſt this Explication of the Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of Faith, to the Grace of Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it hath been alledged, that Faith in Chriſt doth not juſtifie as an act or qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation found in us, but as it hath a peculiar Vertue, not common to Charity, or any other Act of ours; and that is of appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending and receiving Chriſt, or uniting us to him, and ſo making us Partakers of his Righteouſneſs imputed to us, by means whereof we come to be Juſtified, our ſins Covered, and our Souls ſaved.</p>
               <p>Whereunto I anſwer. 1. By allowing an union of Believers with Chriſt the common
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:43236:63"/>Saviour, to be indeed the true ground and foundation of the Benefits which we receive by him. And that this Union is not barely <hi>Relative</hi> or <hi>Political,</hi> ſuch as is betwixt a King, Lord or Husband, and their reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Subjects, Servants and Wives. Nor only <hi>Pactional,</hi> imputed and founded upon the Promiſe or Covenant of the Goſpel, to them that believe in him; but a true and real Union effected by the <hi>Medium</hi> of the Holy Spirit, communicated to them that believe, and are baptized into the Faith of Chriſt. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>For by one Spirit we are all baptized into one Body:</hi> and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>He that is joyned unto the Lord is one Spirit,</hi> ver. 11. of the ſame Chapter, <hi>But ye are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are juſtified, in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of God.</hi> Rom. 8.12. <hi>If any man hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, the ſame is none of his.</hi> This <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt</hi> is ordinarily called <hi>the Spirit of God, abiding or dwelling in all true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, whereby they are partakers of the Divine Nature,</hi> (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh) as Chriſt alſo was,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.16. 1 Cor. 8.19. 2 Pet. 1.4.</note> though not in the ſame meaſure and manner. Such a real
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:43236:64"/>Union there is between Chriſt the Head; and all true Believers, Members of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as there is between the head and members of a natural Body, partaking of one and the ſame natural Spirit. Nor do we deny but that Faith is the firſt Act that diſpoſeth a Man to the <hi>Receipt</hi> of this Divine Spirit dwelling in him, whereby it may be ſaid to effect, or procure our Union with Chriſt, whereby we partake, both of the Nature, and the Effects and Benefits of his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</p>
               <p>But the imputation of Chriſts Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to us is no Scriptural Phraſe, but dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers very much from that of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting not the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, but Faith (working by Charity) to be imputed for Righteouſneſs to them that believe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5, 24. But if it be the act or habit of Faith, which is imputed to us for Righteouſneſs, according to the expreſs literal Senſe of the Apoſtles words, then 'tis not the Perſonal Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, that is imputed to us; for our Faith is no part of his Righteouſneſs. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Phraſe of <hi>Chriſts Righteouſneſs imputed to us,</hi> hath been commonly uſed by Divines of very good Note, amongſt
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:43236:64"/>Proteſtants, (though no man can be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to admit it in a ſtrict Senſe, it being not found in Scripture) yet I think, for Peace ſake, it ſhould not be abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, much leſs with any reflections of Reproach or Diſparagement to them that have uſed it, but rather admitted in ſuch a Candid Senſe, as it may fairly bear. As if the Son of a Prince, or ſome other Perſon of Great Merit and Favour with him, ſhould undertake to be Mediator for ſome Rebel, that had juſtly incurred the Diſpleaſure of his Prince, and rendred himſelf obnoxious to the higheſt penalty of Law, ſhould of his own Good Will, by the Appointment and Will of the Prince, act or ſuffer ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for, and on the behalf of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent, and thereby obtain, by the Grace of the Prince, a free Pardon for him, under ſome equitable Conditions required of the Delinquent. In this caſe the Merits, Act and Sufferings of ſuch a Mediator might, in a reaſonable Senſe, be ſaid to be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Redeemed Perſon. Such an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of this Phraſe of <hi>Chriſts Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs imputed to us,</hi> I think ſhould not be quarrel'd, but may fairly agree with the Scripture phraſes of <hi>Propitiation, Expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:43236:65"/>and Attonement of Chriſt made for us,</hi> and with the Diſcourſe of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. from the 15 Verſe to the end of the Chapter. Other Senſes there are of this Phraſe inſiſted upon by ſome Divines, which cannot be maintained without groſs, and abſurd Conſequences, as hath been ſhewed by ſome that have lately written ſharply concerning this Point.</p>
               <p>This Explication of the Queſtion, what is meant by that Efficacy, which any act, that can be done by us, towards the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of our ſins, or our Juſtification can have, being premiſed, and cleared from the moſt uſual Objections againſt it; I proceed in my Reply to the fore-mentioned Anſwer to the Arguments, for the Confirmation of the Doctrine in hand, drawn from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and Exhortations of Scripture, as followeth.</p>
               <p>To the Firſt part of that Anſwer, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging only the neceſſity of Preſence of Charity and Good Works, together with Faith (in order to the obtainment of the Benefits propounded) as a ſufficient Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for the uſe of thoſe Motives, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſaid Promiſes and Exhortations; I reply, by demanding whether the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:43236:65"/>and Good Works, ſuppoſed to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, do concurr to the Qualification of the Perſon that is to receive theſe Benefits or not: If they do concurr, as any Part of the Qualification of the Perſon, for the <hi>Receipt</hi> of thoſe Benefits, it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by the Explication of the forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Queſtion, but that they are as truly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable to the <hi>Obtainment</hi> of thoſe Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, as Faith, or any thing elſe can be. If they do not concurr, as any Part of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification for theſe Benefits, the bare neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of their Preſence, upon any other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, can be no reaſonable ground of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations to ſuch Actions, in order to the Advantages thereunto promiſed. Nor can thoſe Advantages, or Benefits be any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Motives to ſuch Actions, whiles they are ſuppoſed to contribute nothing at all to the <hi>Obtainment</hi> of them. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, the only deſign of propounding thoſe Motives to ſuch Actions, would be utterly fruſtrate. For all Exhortations, Counſels, or Advices, to any Act or Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, do include this general Suppoſition to common Underſtanding, that the things ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed, or exhorted to, are of ſome Uſe and Validity, to the End that is propounded,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:43236:66"/>either by removing ſome Impediment, or by ſome kind of Cauſality or other; elſe the Advice is altogether vain, and a Man ſhould be never the nearer his End by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing it.</p>
               <p>And therefore it hath been ſaid, that although Charity and Good Works, be in themſelves of no Validity, or Efficacy to the Covering of ſin, Juſtification, or Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of a ſinner, nor do contribute any thing towards the Obtaining of theſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, yet they have the nature of a <hi>Cauſa ſine quâ non,</hi> that is, <hi>of ſomething, without which a thing is not to be effected or gained,</hi> but if that Something hath no manner of Cauſality at all in it, it cannot be called a <hi>Cauſa ſine quâ non,</hi> without a real Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in the Terms. For to be a Cauſe, without which a thing cannot be, and yet to have no manner of Cauſality, in reference to the Effect, is to be a Cauſe and no Cauſe.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe the deſign of the Holy Ghoſt in the forementioned Promiſes, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations had been (as we really ſuppoſe it was) to inſtruct men what they ſhould do, or what things poſſible to be done by them, would be available to the ends
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:43236:66"/>propounded. I demand how ſuch a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign could have been expreſſed, more ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificantly then it is by the Terms uſed in the Exhortations and Promiſes alledged. And as for the bare neceſſity of preſence of Charity and Good Works, together with Faith in the Perſons which are to be juſtified and ſaved, that's no more then is equally true of the faculties of Life, Senſe, and Reaſon, there being a perfect neceſſity of the preſence of all theſe things to the act of Faith, which is ſuppoſed to be the only thing that juſtifies a man. But would it therefore be reaſonable to exhort men to take care to preſerve theſe faculties in order to their Juſtification, or might the Promiſes of Pardon of Sin, Life, and Salvation be reaſonably annexed to ſuch a care of preſerving theſe Faculties, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bare account of their neceſſary preſence, or concomitancy, with a juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faith.</p>
               <p>Now where it hath been ſaid, that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Good Works are neceſſary to the verification of that Faith, by which we are juſtified, <hi>i. e.</hi> to declare and manifeſt the truth of it, but have otherwiſe no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current Efficacy to the Juſtification of the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:43236:67"/>Believer, and that is a ſufficient account of the reaſonableneſs of all Promiſes made to the habit and exerciſe of this Vertue, as alſo of the Exhortations before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. I anſwer, that if indeed theſe things be neceſſary to the verification of that Faith that juſtifies us, ſo as to conſtitute and make up the Truth and Validity thereof, and thereby to declare the Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy thereof, the Queſtion is really yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; And theſe things muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to have a concurrent Efficacy to the forementioned Effect, which is all that is contended for.</p>
               <p>But if by the verification of Faith no more be meant, then a bare manifeſtation of the truth of it, by the Signs and Fruits of it, that is the ſame thing with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer allegation, concerning the neceſſity or uſefulneſs of theſe things, for the Aſſurance of a mans Juſtification or Salvation. But whether this be the true intent, or only meaning of the Promiſes, and Exhortations made to theſe Practices, I appeal to the Judgment of any Unprejudiced Reader, that ſhall review, and conſider the expreſs Terms and Forms of Words uſed in them.</p>
               <p>When we pray for the Forgiveneſs of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:43236:67"/>our ſins, muſt this be the only Meaning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r not that God will be pleaſed to forgive us, upon any conſideration of our Prayers, but that he will give us an Aſſurance, that he hath forgiven us? I appeal to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of any of them, that make this Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation (to ſerve an Hypotheſis, which they have unwarily eſpouſed) whether this hath been, or is their own Senſe in their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for the Pardon of their ſin. Which is no other, then if a Criminal, petitioning a King for his Pardon, ſhould thereby intend not to obtain it, but only to be aſſured that it was granted. When our Saviour promiſeth, that <hi>if we will forgive Men their Treſpaſſes, our Heavenly Father will alſo forgive us our Treſpaſſes,</hi> is that his only Meaning, that our Forgiving others ſhall be to us a ſign, and evidence that we are forgiven, but no Means to obtain that Forgiveneſs? When we are exhorted to Repentance for the Remiſſion of our ſins, which was the common Doctrine of the Prophets, of <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt, our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and his Apoſtles, and particularly of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in anſwer to the Queſtion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> what they ſhould do to be ſaved, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.30. was this their Meaning, not to
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:43236:68"/>teach Men to repent, to that end that they might be ſaved, and their ſins be forgiven them, but that they might be aſſured that their ſins were forgiven them? I deſire any Indifferent Reader, that is not pertinaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly bent to maintain a Prejudice againſt all Appearance of Reaſon, to apply this Meaning to the Promiſes, Exhortations, and Aſſertions of Scripture, which have been before alledged to this Purpoſe, and then to judge, whether all, or any of them be to be interpreted to this Sence. And if they be, I demand why the ſame promiſes of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, Salvation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> made to the act of Faith, may not, or ſhould not admit of the ſame Interpretation (as ſome of the Antinomians have contended) <hi>viz.</hi> that Faith it ſelf contributes nothing at all to any of theſe Effects or Benefits, that are thereunto promiſed, or is any Means or Condition of obtaining them, but only a ſign or means to aſſure us of our Intereſt in them.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I demand, whether any thing poſſible to be done by us, doth ſerve to qualifie us for the <hi>Reception</hi> of thoſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, by the Grace of God, or be of any Validity, or moral Efficacy towards the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:43236:68"/>of theſe Ends? If not, then Faith can be of no more Efficacy to this purpoſe then Charity. But if any Act or Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is poſſible to be performed by us, be any ways effectual or available to theſe Ends, why may not Charity, (eſpecially as a fruit and effect of Faith) be conceived to have a concurrent Efficacy with Faith, or ſubordinate to it, agreeable to the many promiſes of the ſame Benefits made to Charity and Good Works, as well as to Faith? And ſeeing that it is, and muſt be ever acknowledged, that it is only of the free Grace of God, that Faith is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted as any condition, qualification, or means of obtaining theſe Benefits; Seeing alſo, that Charity, in the proper nature of it, is the moſt Excellent, and moſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Vertue, moſt conformable to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God himſelf, and therefore ſaid to be the greateſt of the three Chriſtian Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13. Is it not very reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to believe that ſuch a quality moſt Divine, expreſſing both the Nature and Image of God, and being alſo the Effect of his own free Grace, ſhould be accepted as part of that diſpoſition in us, that qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifies us for his Favour and Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:43236:69"/>merited only by the Expiatory Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and Obedience of his Son, always acknowledged by our Faith in him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing all confidence in any thing that we can do, as acceptable upon any other account, then of his Meritorious Meciation?</p>
               <p>Other reaſons are given by Modern Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the Proteſtant Party, concerning the neceſſity of Charity and Good Works, excluſive of this we contend for; alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that theſe things are neceſſary <hi>neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate praecepti, non medii, i. e.</hi> neceſſary parts of our Duty, in obedience to the Law, or Will of God, not neceſſary means of Salvation, or obtaining the Benefit of remiſſion of our ſins, neceſſary to be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, in order to the pleaſing of God, the Glorifying and Honouring of his Name, to expreſs our Thankfulneſs to him for all his Benefits, eſpecially for his Free Grace of Redemption and Juſtification, procured by the merits of Chriſt: As alſo neceſſary to adorn our Holy Profeſſion, the Honour of Chriſt and his Goſpel, to give Good Example, and avoid Scandal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which are without Exception to be acknowledged, for juſt Reaſons of our Duty: But do fignifie nothing to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:43236:69"/>the Queſtion in hand, in as much as they do not ſeverally, or jointly make any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable account, either of the promiſes of Pardon, Eternal Life, and Salvation, to the performances of theſe Duties, or of the Exhortations to the practice of them, urged by ſuch Promiſes. Theſe Reaſons are indeed juſt Motives to the Duties of Piety and Charity, and urged as ſuch, in other Texts of Scripture. But of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ſort and nature from thoſe which are propounded in the Promiſes and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations alledged by us. Theſe Reaſons with others of like import (excluſive of that which is urged by us) alledged as the only account of the neceſſity of Good Works, do utterly deſtroy and make void the validity of the Motives, in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Promiſes.</p>
               <p>And here (with as little diſparagement as may be to the Author) I think it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me to mention the great diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, not to ſay Scandal, which I long ſince took from the common outlandiſh <hi>Catechiſm</hi> ſet forth firſt by <hi>Zachary <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin,</hi> and afterward by <hi>David Paraeus,</hi> Anno D. 1623. who intitles the third part of his Book, wherein he undertakes to give an
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:43236:70"/>account of the neceſſity of Good Works, and all the practical part of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>de Gratitudine, of Gratitude</hi> or Thankfulneſs to God for our Deliverance from the miſery of the Natural State, and our Liberty recovered by Chriſt, which are the titles of his two former parts. This General Title and Account of Good Works, doth plainly ſuppoſe a negation of any antecedent neceſſity of Converſion and Repentance (which are the two firſt things which he treats of under that Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Thankfulneſs) unto the Effect of our Juſtification and Salvation; unleſs it be reaſonable to ſay, that a man is obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be thankfull for a Benefit before he hath it, or to the end that he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it. Converſion unto God, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance by this mans Doctrine, muſt be looked upon as a thing not in it ſelf ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to our Juſtification or Remiſſion of ſin, but as a Duty of Gratitude, for this Grace given unto us, either before, or without reſpect to our Converſion. And we are to repent, and turn to God, not that our ſins may be forgiven, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſo; not that we may be ſaved, but becauſe we believe, and are
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:43236:70"/>confident that we ſhall be ſaved. So the whole practice of Chriſtian Piety, Holineſs and Righteouſneſs before God, muſt proceed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an account of Thankfulneſs to him, for his free Grace that requires none of theſe things at our hands, as conditions of our Pardon or Reconciliation with his offended Majeſty.</p>
               <p>Not but that ſome other Ends and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and particularly thoſe which we men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before, are alſo named by the ſame Author, as part of the neceſſity of Good Works. But all are reduced unto the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral account of Thankfulneſs, and exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of any Moral cauſality, or condition of Juſtification and Salvation. How well this Doctrine agrees with Natural Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the Scriptures of the Old Teſtament, or even with the deſign of the Goſpel; I muſt leave to be judged by indifferent Readers. Becauſe I hold not my ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged in this place to engage any further in the great Controverſie, about Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by Faith alone, or to take parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular notice of the Texts of St. <hi>Paul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly alledged, for the Solifidian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; which have been exactly conſidered by ſo many of our own Divines; and my own Senſe of them elſewhere delivered in
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:43236:71"/>brief. Beſides that the covering of ſins attributed to Charity in the preſent Text, though it extends to the Effect of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in the moſt Eminent Senſe of the Phraſe; yet is not by our Interpretation, limited to that ſignification, but extended (as hath been ſaid) to the removal of puniſhments in this life, and to the abatement of them, both in this Life, and that which is to come, which are the Benefits that may be obtained by Charity, without any perfect Juſtification of a ſinner.</p>
               <p>Now if any Perſon that reads this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, having not been prepoſſeſſed with any Prejudice againſt this Doctrine, or doubt of the Truth of it, ſhall think that the Work is over-done, by the Allegation of ſo many Texts and Arguments for the Confirmation of it, and ſo much pains ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in anſwering Objections againſt it, and ſhall therefore charge me with loading the Readers with a tedious Accumulation of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous Arguments, thereby abating the Perſpicuity of the Matter, as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpeaks, upon occaſion of his long Diſcourſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Perſpicuitas enim argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione elevatur, —Remque meâ ſententiâ minimè dubiam, argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentando dubiam facis.</hi> Tull. <hi>de Oratore Lib.</hi> 3.</note> to prove the Exiſtence of a Deity. I muſt
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:43236:71"/>anſwer, that this Objection, can only be made by him that is ignorant of the contrary Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, commonly aſſerted and contended for, not only by Lutherans and Calviniſts abroad, but by ſeveral of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Divines (till of late years) going that way. And 2. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the bad Conſequences of that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine have been ſtrongly averted by the Authors thereof, in ſome of their Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet the Event and Effect thereof hath, to my own Knowledge, in a multitude of Perſons, with whom I have had Occaſion to converſe, notoriouſly abated the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Charity, and the Zeal or Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Good Works, ſuppoſed by this Doctrine, to be neither abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor available to the Salvation of a Chriſtian. Many Perſons I have known, who upon this only Ground, have negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and ſlighted the practice of Charity, not only in their Life time, but alſo at their Death, comforting themſelves againſt all fear of Peril by this Neglect, from a miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Notion, and Confidence of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Faith alone, without Good Works.</p>
               <p>The Senſe of this dangerous Errour, was one thing that moved me to the Pains of this Plain Diſcourſe. Having viſited di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:43236:72"/>Perſons in their Laſt ſickneſs, earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moving them (according to the Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Church Liturgy in that Office) to Liberality towards the Poor, with little or no Succeſs, upon a Miſperſwaſion of the no Neceſſity, and as little Validity of ſuch Works to the ſafety of their future State.</p>
               <p>And though I have known Some, and do believe there are many of that Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that upon other Conſiderations, and better Principles, have been very Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Forward to Good Works; yet I have alſo had a particular Opportunity of obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp; Knowing ſomething more than other Men, concerning the Neglect of this Duty, from the Place of my late Habitation for ſome Years, belonging to an Office of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtry, kept for the Probate, and Cuſtody of Wills and Teſtaments, made within the Juriſdiction of the Arch-deacon of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk:</hi> wherein I have obſerved this laſt Record and Teſtimony of Charity, which ſhould have made up the Neglect and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of that Duty before; to have been either wholly omitted, or very penuriouſly, and diſproportionably expreſſed in many, and indeed moſt Wills of Conſiderable Eſtates.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:43236:72"/>
               <p>But to take off all appearance of Scandal to our Religion, upon this Account, it hath been, or may be made Evident, upon a juſt Reckoning, that the Publick Good Works, and <hi>Donations</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to pious Uſes in this Nation, ſince the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> have been more than Equal to any that ever were done by Papiſts, within the ſame Compaſs of Time, in any precedent Age: This perſonal Apology for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſcourſe, might perhaps have been ſpared; but was piouſly intended to the beſt Advantage, and greateſt Concern of all Perſons in the time of their Life, and at their Death. There being certainly no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Uſe to be made of Worldly Goods ſo Acceptable to God, or ſo Advantagious to the Owners thereof, both in their Lives, and at their Death, as that which I am la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to promote from this Text.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
